<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions, being the two last books of my reverend brother Mr. Williams the one entituled A postscript to Gospel-truth, the other An end of discord : conscientiously examined, in order to a free entertainment of the truth, in some momentous points in divinity, controverted among the nonconformist brethen, occasionally here determined, for the sake of those honest among us that seek it, without trick or partiality / by John Humfrey ...</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12859443</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12859443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions, being the two last books of my reverend brother Mr. Williams the one entituled A postscript to Gospel-truth, the other An end of discord : conscientiously examined, in order to a free entertainment of the truth, in some momentous points in divinity, controverted among the nonconformist brethen, occasionally here determined, for the sake of those honest among us that seek it, without trick or partiality / by John Humfrey ...</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Snowden, for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 38.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716. --  Gospel-truth stated and vindicated. --  Postscript.</term>
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716. --  End to discord.</term>
               <term>Justification.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94653:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94653:1"/>
            <p>Animadverſions: BEING The Two Laſt BOOKS OF MY Reverend Brother Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> The One Entituled, <hi>A Poſtſcript to Goſpel-Truth:</hi> The Other, <hi>An End of Diſcord.</hi> Conſcientiouſly Examined. In Order to a Free Entertainment of the <hi>Truth,</hi> in ſome Momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Points in Divinity, controverted among the Nonconformiſt Brethren, occaſionally here Determined, for the ſake of thoſe Honeſt among Us that ſeek it, without Trick, or Partiality.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Humfrey,</hi> the Aged.</p>
            <q>
               <p>What thy Hand findeth to do, do it with thy Might: For there is no Work, nor Device, nor Wiſdom in the Grave whither thou goeſt,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 9.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Snowden,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three Crowns,</hi> the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:94653:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94653:2"/>
            <head>Animadverſions on his Poſtſcript.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Introduction.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>WIlliams</hi> having Printed his Book called <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> with many <hi>Presbyterian</hi> hands ſet to it, there was ſome heat, and ſeveral Exceptions raiſed againſt it, by ſome of the <hi>Independent</hi> Brethren; whereof one of the chief was this, That he held the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to be imputed only in the Effects. Here, inſtead of his owning this Truth, and ſtanding to it, he denies that he held it, and for his proof, produces this paſſage out of his Book, That <hi>beſides the Effects being made ours, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to Believers.</hi> This paſſage of his I took, and gave him notice of, in a Letter Printed in my <hi>Middle Way of Juſtification,</hi> diſliking it as receding from Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> to uphold himſelf againſt this <hi>Accuſation,</hi> is unhappily engaged, and ſets his Wits in his <hi>Man made Righteous,</hi> to from a notion that might ſerve him to maintain his own Doctrine (which is <hi>Baxterian</hi>) and yet anſwer the <hi>Brethren,</hi> as he has, by this denial, and ſo ſatisfie his followers. A great conceit at preſent I perceive he took of his Notion (which ſhews him honeſt) by that paſſage in the <hi>Sheet</hi> he called an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my <hi>Letter,</hi> where he complains of <hi>his being ſtruck at by both Extreams, when deeper thoughts</hi> (ſays he) <hi>would perceive the Truth ſtated</hi> (quoting p. 77, 78, 79, 80. of that Book) <hi>againſt the exceſs of both.</hi> The Brethren and common Proteſtant ſay, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and I, that it is imputed, and can be made ours only, <hi>quoad Effectus.</hi> Either the <hi>Brethren</hi> or <hi>We</hi> are in the right: But Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> has an inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to middle the matter ſo, as we ſhall both be out, and in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream; and yet he hold with us both. Theſe <hi>deeper thoughts</hi> therefore of his I took into conſideration, in my Book called <hi>Pacification,</hi> and he offering ſomething in reply in ſome other <hi>after</hi> Books, I took it again into conſideration in my <hi>Appendix</hi> To my laſt book: But finding this Reverend Brother keeping ſtill his courſe, in <hi>holding with the Hound,</hi> (as the Proverb is) and <hi>running with the Hare,</hi> I muſt purſue him in his Notion, till I have hunted it down: For it is a cloudy, perplexed trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Notion, that can ſerve us nothing but to entangle the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, without any profit to others, or ſignificancy to himſelf. As I have made my Animadverſions therefore on his Books preceding, I do make theſe on theſe later Books, ſeeing he perſiſts in his Notion, which were writ in two Letters; the firſt to himſelf, the ſecond to another, and are as follows.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94653:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Reading your Poſtſcript, I come in <hi>p.</hi> 525. to the Point, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Goſpel be a <hi>Law,</hi> and I turned to your <hi>Defence,</hi> as you bid, for your ſenſe of it; where you ſhew in what ſenſe you allow it, and in what you do not. As for the ſenſe in which you allow it, and then maintain the ſame with your Reaſons I approve; but as to the ſenſe wherein you do not allow it, though I except not againſt the reſt, I make a ſtand at the ſecond, to wit, the ſenſe you ſay our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines fix upon the <hi>Arminians,</hi> and upon that prejudice do you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it, when if you had not miſcited it, you had as well yield to your Adverſaries, that it is no Law at all, as to deny this ſenſe of it. I ſay therefore in oppoſition to you, <hi>The Goſpel is a Law in this ſenſe, that acts of Obedience to it</hi> (that is a ſincere, or ſound Faith working by Love, which it requires) <hi>is the Righteouſneſs</hi> (when perform'd) <hi>by which we are juſtified, as perfect Obedience was under the Law of Adam.</hi> You do this harmleſs, honeſt, and right tenent, open wrong in ſaying <hi>[for which].</hi> the <hi>Arminians,</hi> as well as we, do all know, that it is Chriſt's Satisfaction and Merit, (not ours) is that <hi>for</hi> which we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, but it is our Faith it ſelf (the Faith which is the condition of the Goſpel, that is, St. <hi>Jame</hi>'s Faith, and Works alſo) is that Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs (when perform'd) which conſtitutes us righteous, and <hi>by which</hi> we are juſtified.</p>
            <p>Pray Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> believe it, and be confirm'd, that as perfect Obedience was the Condition of Life in the Law of Works; and if that Condition had been performed, it had been <hi>Adams</hi> Righteouſneſs by which he had been juſtified: so is Faith the Condition of the Law of Grace; and if that Condition be fulfilled, it does become a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs according to this Law, ſo as by it we are juſtified. In the <hi>one</hi> (I muſt add, to prevent what you may alledge) the reward would have been of <hi>Merit</hi> or <hi>Debt,</hi> becauſe it was for the <hi>performance ſake:</hi> In the other it is of <hi>Grace,</hi> becauſe it is for <hi>Chriſts ſake</hi> that it is ſo accepted.</p>
            <p>I was ſorry at my heart that in the Letters between me and my Learned, holy, humble and worthy Brother Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> though no Man be more for Conditions under the Goſpel than he, and that the Goſpel is a Law, and that Law by which we ſhall be judged; yet did he ſtick at yielding this, which is ſo open and undeniably conſequent, to wit, that whatſoever it be which is required by a Law, as the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof before it is fulfilled, when that Condition is fulfilled, it does, and muſt become the Righteouſneſs of that Law, and if a Man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94653:3"/>be judged thereby, he muſt be juſtified. It is that very Righteouſneſs is the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of his Juſtification: For that there muſt be ſome <hi>Juſtitia,</hi> wherein <hi>Juſtificationis forma</hi> does <hi>Conſtare;</hi> there is no Man's Reaſon but muſt how. <hi>Being a Condition, it is a Righteouſneſs as to Judicial proceedings, by that Law which appoints that Condition,</hi> ſay you, <hi>p.</hi> 274.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faith</hi> (Def. <hi>p.</hi> 22.) <hi>is not the Juſtifying Righteouſneſs, but is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our being juſtified by Chriſts Righteouſneſs.</hi> By ſuch expreſſions contradicting this before, what mean you? You pretend (at leaſt one may think ſo) to ſpeak as the common <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> but do you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand as they? to wit, that upon our believing, Chriſts Righteouſneſs is ſo imputed as to be legally ours, for our Juſtification? If you believe not this, why do you not ſay quite otherwiſe? That tho' it is Chriſts Righteouſneſs is the meritorious cauſe of our Juſtification, and ſo the Righteouſneſs <hi>for which;</hi> yet it is Faith is the Juſtifying Righteouſneſs, or that Righteouſneſs <hi>by which</hi> we are juſtified.</p>
            <p>Do not you again concur (<hi>p.</hi> 258.)? <hi>Seeing the Goſpel is a Law promiſing pardon and life to all ſuch as believe (to be exerciſed in vertue of Chriſts Obedience) it is Faith, being the performed Condition, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us for Righteouſneſs,</hi> or is that upon which God accounts us righteous, and ſo theſe benefits thereby belong to us. <hi>Juſtification being a forinſick act</hi> (ſay you more fully, <hi>p.</hi> 276.) <hi>that, upon which the Law a Man is tried by, doth acquit him from its threatned penalty, and entitles him to is promiſed benefits, is ſo far Juſtifying Righteouſneſs by that Law.</hi> An impartial acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 263. You ſtate a difference which you have, or make with others, by the Queſtion; <hi>Whether the Death of Chriſt is legally eſteemed to be endured by us, and his Obedience by us to be performed: Or whether they are imputed to Believers as their pleadable ſecurity for their pardon and title to Eternal Life in the right of Chriſt?</hi> Here you ſay the former they affirm, and you deny; the latter you affirm, and they deay. But ſee what it is to be fudled with a Notion, and that ſuch as diſturbs the brain more than ſtrong Drink. There is not, and never was any ſuch queſtion and difference broached by any but your ſelf. It is true, that as to the <hi>former,</hi> the <hi>Antinomian</hi> maintains, but you deny, and upon Reaſons that are good. For if that were ſo, then muſt the Believer be in Gods ſight as righteous as Chriſt (as you argue) and that is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with pardon. But when you ſay as to the <hi>latter,</hi> that you affirm, and they deny it, I pray where is the Man that ever oppoſed you, or once thought of the matter to deny it? Who ever beſides you made ſuch a Diſtribution? Who ever before you offered this Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94653:4"/>Chriſts performance of the Covenant of Redemption does afford us a pleadable ſecurity, that if we believe and repent, we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Why do you pretend a difference with any in this matter, that no body ever queſtioned, or perhaps thought on? <hi>How can Mr. H. deny</hi> (ſay you, <hi>p.</hi> 269.) <hi>ſuch a pleadable ſecurity?</hi> Why Mr. <hi>H.</hi> denies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not, and none elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Let this which you teach us, and we never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered before be granted, how does this prove the Point, that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt therefore is imputed to us otherwiſe than in the Effects? It is imputed to us for our pleadable ſecurity. Be it ſo, and is not that pleadable ſecurity an Effect of Chriſts performance? It is, we muſt both acknowledge it, and do we not agree in this, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is indeed imputed to us in the Effects? Where is the difference? We both aſſert that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is no <hi>Legally</hi> to be eſteemed ours, and neither of us deny this <hi>pleadable ſecurity to</hi> be every true Believers. How then do we differ? This pleadable ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is not Chriſts Righteouſneſs it ſelf, is it? It is an <hi>Effect</hi> ariſing from it, is it not? How then does this make good your aſſertion, that <hi>Beſides the Effects the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed,</hi> when it makes out no more, but that here is an <hi>Effect,</hi> in regard to which it is imputed, or which the Believer has by vertue of it? <hi>He that enjoys a benefit as merited for him by anothers act, be hath that act imputed to him as his pleadable ſecurity, for his poſſeſſing that merited bleſſing,</hi> you ſay, and I ſay ſo too, that is, imputed in regard to that <hi>Effect,</hi> and no otherwiſe than ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 268. <hi>The application of Chriſts Death to Believers, Gods Judicial accounting them the perſons in whom the Promiſe made to Chriſt is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and his giving them pardon and eternal life as the merited Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his Death and Obedience, gives juſt ground for us to ſay the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to Believers.</hi> I ſay no, all this ſtraining will not do. It is indeed a ground and proof that it is imputed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the <hi>Effects,</hi> but not otherwiſe. You add, <hi>they do not only enjoy pardon and ſuch Effects, but his Righteouſneſs it ſelf is imputed to them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively in that pardon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Sir! Are you come hither? How much more ingenuous had it been then for you to make the acknowledgment of your coming up here to me and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and ſaid plainly, that though you have ſaid, that <hi>Beſides the Effects made ours, the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to Believers;</hi> you mean nothing but as we do, or your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is but this, that the Effects being indeed made ours, his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is <hi>relatively only</hi> to be ſaid ours in regard to thoſe Effects.</p>
            <p>In my Book (<hi>Ult. Man. p.</hi> 5.) ſuppoſing there the Queſtion, what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94653:4"/>we are to apprehend by the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, which is no Scripture expreſſion; I ſay there are theſe two things in it. <hi>The one is, that God did indeed account or allow of what Chriſt did and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be in our behalf, for our ſakes, for us, in our ſtead, as to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petration of the benefits we have by him upon condition: And the other is, our having thoſe benefits as to the Application upon the performance; and that is, the having his Righteouſneſs to be ours, Really in the Effects, and Relatively in regard to them.</hi> In my Appendix to you (<hi>p.</hi> 83.) I have the ſame, where asking how the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is, or can be ours, or reckoned to us as ours; I anſwer, <hi>The Effects are ours Really, and his Righteouſneſs ours Relatively, in regard to thoſe Effects.</hi> I do not doubt but I can find in ſome Book of Mr. <hi>Baxters,</hi> words to the ſame purpoſe, or theſe ſame words. When we three then thus agree, why ſhould not you, being put upon it, and brought into the caſe of confeſſion, have acknowledged this Agreement as to us, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement with the Brethren; for herein it is wherein Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath broke looſe from the commonly received Doctrine of the Proteſtants, who have ſtill talked of Chriſts Righteouſneſs it ſelf to be the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, which they meant all (even the <hi>Antinomian</hi> that is learned) on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Legally,</hi> and we ſay not ſo, but <hi>Relatively</hi> only, in regard to the <hi>Effects.</hi> How then comes it to paſs, that in ſo many places in your Books you bring in the Charm of <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs imputed</hi> (and as it were ſometimes by head and ſhoulders) as it ſeems purpoſely to make folks believe, as if you were one that maintained the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with your <hi>Brethren,</hi> whom you oppoſe? How can this paſs, and not appear to be without ſincerity, ſo long as you are not of their mind?</p>
            <p>As for what you elſe have in this Poſtſcript that may concern me, I would ſay ſomething more particularly to, if I could gather it up, and digeſt it. You diſtinguiſh between the Covenant of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Law, and Law of the <hi>Goſpol.</hi> Of the <hi>one</hi> you ſay well, that Chriſt only is the Subject, and that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it in order to the <hi>Impetration</hi> of the benefits we have by his Life and Death, or by his Redemption. Of the other we are all Subjects, and are to perform it our ſelves in order to the <hi>Application</hi> of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, or participation of thoſe benefits he hath obtained for us. This Diſtinction (whether neceſſary or no, (for I think it to be of our own late Divines, and no antient one) is good ſo far as thus uſed: But as for your Notion which you ſo induſtriouſly build upon it, though it hath ſomething of truth in it, it is too perplext, over-loading, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, ſo that it edifies not. For why, I pray, do you trouble your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94653:5"/>ſelf and us with this teaching, that we have a pleadable ſecurity from Gods Promiſe to Chriſt in his Covenant of Redemption, that if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve we ſhall be ſaved, when we have an expreſs Promiſe thereof to every one our ſelves in the Goſpel, and is not that ſecurity enough, if this moreover had not been ſtarted by you?</p>
            <p>It is apparent, that ſeeing the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which you count to be imputed to us, Is his performance of the <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Law, this is a Righteouſneſs whereof we are uncapable, and conſequently not that Righteouſneſs which the common <hi>Proteſtant</hi> hath accounted to be imputed, or made ours (in their ſenſe) for our Juſtification. It muſt yet be acknowledged, that the Righteouſneſs of the Law of Works which we were bound to perform, is part of that <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Law which he performed, and I ſuppoſe the common <hi>Proteſtant</hi> have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that part thereof conſiſting in his active and paſſive Obedience, to be the Righteouſneſs which is imputed to Believers: And here it is certain, that you fall not in with them in this Opinion, but hold that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt which you call our <hi>Juſtifying Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that which <hi>beſides the Effects</hi> (as you ſpeak) <hi>is imputed to the Believer,</hi> is his <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Righteouſneſs, as appears by your expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, when you ſay, <hi>it is imputed to Believers as their pleadable ſecurity for their pardon and title to eternal life, in the Right of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Right of Chriſt,</hi> this makes it plain, that you underſtand his <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Righteouſneſs; but I hope you do not ſtill mean that the ſame numerical <hi>Right</hi> which is his, can be ours. You know the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of one subject cannot migrate into another, ſo that <hi>Really</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; and if you grant it to be <hi>Legally</hi> ours, take heed leſt you grant all away, for then may your Brethren ſay, Chriſts performance it ſelf is ours alſo in that ſenſe, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and I and you are gone. But not to ſtop (this being only in the way) the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt you mean being his <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Righteouſneſs, you account then that there is a <hi>ſubordinate</hi> Righteouſneſs which we muſt have in order to the Imputation of this to us for our Juſtification. Hereupon you ſet up two <hi>Barrs,</hi> the Barr of the <hi>Law,</hi> and Barr of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> the <hi>Creators</hi> Barr, and the <hi>Redeemers</hi> Barr, as you call them, inſomuch as together with a double Righteouſneſs and double Barr, you make us alſo (as any one may think) two Specifical Juſtifications: But not after this narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if the Diſtinction you laid down before be tight, that the Law whereto Chriſt ſubjected himſelf in order to the Impetration of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption was the <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Law, and his performance of that Law our Juſtifying Righteouſneſs, according as you affirm, then can there be no <hi>Creators</hi> Barr, or Barr of the Law of <hi>Works</hi> here erected for us
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94653:5"/>to ſtand at, ſeeing it was Chriſt alone was accountable for that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</p>
            <p>And further, ſeeing Chriſt, as he took on him our Nature, did vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily come alſo under the <hi>Law,</hi> (the Law of <hi>Works,</hi> as well as <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law), as part of his Fathers Commandment, and perfectly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the ſame, and ſuffered moreover for our tranſgreſſing it; he did thereby as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>redeem us from the Law.</hi> And what I pray is this Redemption from that Law, but a delivering us fromits <hi>Barr</hi> (if you underſtand the thing) ſo as we are not to be <hi>judged</hi> by it. Though we are under the Law ſtill as a Rule of <hi>Living,</hi> we are freed from it as the Rule of <hi>Judgment,</hi> as I ſay in my <hi>Pacification.</hi> Again, I muſt inculcate upon this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> the Law of <hi>Mediation,</hi> being that Law Chriſt performed for the Impetration of thoſe benefits which we have by him, and the law of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> that we perform for Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe benefits; I pray let me ask, is not Juſtification one of thoſe benefits Chriſt hath impetrated, merited, purchaſed for us? As Pardon and Salvation, ſo are <hi>Juſtification,</hi> (whereof theſe are Effects,) and the <hi>Law of Grace</hi> it ſelf which juſtifies us, all of them benefits that Chriſt hath purchaſed by performing the Law of Mediation. Well, Juſtification then it ſelf being one of thoſe benefits, when Chriſts performance of the <hi>Mediatorial</hi> Law is that Righteouſneſs alone which goes to the <hi>Impetration</hi> of it; and in this regard that may be ſaid ours: It is our performance of the Law of Grace which goes to, and is the Righteouſneſs alone which is, or can be ours in the <hi>Application,</hi> or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it.</p>
            <p>To come at laſt then to a full point in this matter, it being Chriſts performance, which we agree, hath merited, impetrated, procured all our benefits, and ſo is the <hi>Principal</hi> Righteouſneſs (as you may call it if you pleaſe) when yet there muſt be a Righteouſneſs of our own to go before, as the Condition which this Law of the Goſpel requires of us to give us right to theſe benefits, it appears in what ſenſe our Faith or Evangelical Obedience is to be held a Righteouſneſs <hi>ſubordinate</hi> (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath ſo termed it) unto Chriſts, which is no more than this, that our Goſpel Righteouſneſs of Faith is prerequired in order to the having the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt <hi>imputed,</hi> according to you and Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> But how imputed, for here is the upſhot? Does Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> mean imputed <hi>in ſe</hi> beſides the <hi>Effects,</hi> as you ſpeak? No, this were to make it <hi>Legally</hi> ours and he allows no Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs in any ſenſe of its being made ours but <hi>Relatively</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Effects only: So that if the phraſe of the <hi>Imputing Chriſts Righteouſneſs</hi> was left out altogether of our Books (as it is in our Bibles)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94653:6"/>and our Divines had ſaid nothing but that upon our believing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, we are for Chriſts ſake, and through the Law of Grace made partakers of the benefits he hath purchaſed, and ſo of Pardon and Life (the Doctrine of Satisfaction wherein we agree, being firſt Preached), the Article of Juſtification might have been explained well enough for honeſt Peoples Edification.</p>
            <p>P. 279. <hi>Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> (you ſhould ſay <hi>though,</hi> and not by), <hi>and Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs of Faith, are ſo connected and inſeparable in the ſubject, that they are expreſſed as if but one only Act, and yet they are very diſtinguiſhable.</hi> Having laid down what precedes, I do as it were give inſtance in this Citation, unto the which I do the more deliberately anſwer. The <hi>Impetration</hi> of our Juſtification by Chriſts performing the <hi>Mediatory</hi> Law is indeed one thing, and the <hi>Application</hi> of it by our performing the Law of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is another: But Juſtification it ſelf is one <hi>(Omneens eſt unum)</hi> and not two things, or acts, and conſequently ought to be defined and underſtood as one act; ſo that when in one place it is ſaid we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Chriſts <hi>Blood</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, through his Blood), and in others we are juſtified by <hi>Faith,</hi> this makes yet but one act, one Juſtification de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in one place by the <hi>meritorious,</hi> in the others by the <hi>formal</hi> cauſe thereof, which both are to be put together in the Definition.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> as I remember, does ordinarily ſpeak at your rate, as if we were to be juſtified both by Law and Goſpel; and furthermore does not ſcruple to make as many Particular Juſtifications as there can be Charges laid againſt us, but with the aſſertion that there is alſo a Juſtification Univerſal, and which I apprehend the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel alone does yield us. Indeed how to reconcile Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> herein to his own Doctrine, I muſt confeſs I have not yet obſerved from him, but crave your help to find out. In the mean time I muſt warn you that you underſtand him not after the manner you write; for if indeed there are two <hi>Barrs</hi> at which we muſt be juſtified, as well as two <hi>Righteouſneſſes</hi> that goes into our Juſtification: If to be juſtified by <hi>Faith</hi> is one Juſtification, and to be juſtified by <hi>Chriſts Blood</hi> be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that the Believer muſt have both, as one <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to the other, unto which apprehenſion your way of expreſſion leads; then muſt Chriſts Righteouſneſs be indeed ours <hi>in ſe,</hi> and not only in the <hi>Effects,</hi> as you appear to maintain againſt me and him, for at one of theſe, <hi>Barrs</hi> nothing leſs will ſerve, and then muſt we return all three to the Road of the common Proteſtant Doctrine, and grant that it is not by our own Works, whether Legal or Evangelical, no not by Faith as a Work, not by Faith as productive of Repentance and New
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94653:6"/>Obedience, that is not by St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Faith and Works alſo,</hi> but by <hi>Faith only,</hi> and by Faith taken <hi>objective,</hi> for Chriſts Righteouſneſs made ours by Faith, ſo as to be our Formal Righteouſneſs, or formally to juſtifie us. And if ſo, there may be an <hi>end of Controverſies</hi> with Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Books (as one of them is called) which concern Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, his Practical Books may ſtill be in credit, but his Controverſal Works may be all burnt for you, who for maintaining one expreſſion, not well adviſed, muſt forſake him, and your ſelf, and all almoſt of weight, that you have writ beſides. There is a Diſtinction therefore which that accurate Man Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who otherwiſe has ſo many, does yet want as to this Point of Juſtification, which is, that Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be taken <hi>Strictly</hi> or <hi>Largely,</hi> ſeeing the Scripture ſo ſpeaks of it. If we will take it <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> we conſider only what reſpects the form and definition, and Juſtification ſo taken, is Gods conſtituting (by his Law of Grace) and accounting a Man righteous upon his believing for Chriſts ſake, or imputing his Faith for Righteouſneſs: When Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification <hi>largely</hi> taken, may comprehend its <hi>Antecedents</hi> (as Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and <hi>Conſequents</hi> (as Pardon and Life) together with it. See my <hi>Righteouſneſs of God, p.</hi> 55, 56, 57. In ſuch a large ſenſe of it. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and our Divines may take liberty to ſpeak of it in ſuch a manner as they or others do, or as they pleaſe; but there are theſe words in that Learned Gentleman Sir <hi>Charles Wolſley,</hi> his Letter to me, that are more accurate to my purpoſe, than any that I moſt like in Mr. <hi>Baxter. The Scripture</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that were written not with any relation to thoſe nice and ſubtle Diſtinctions which Men have ſince uſed in interpreting them, do chiefly intend to expreſs their plain and genuine meaning of things, and in an eſpecial manner by various expreſſions of the ſame thing does ſet forth the amplitude of Goſpel Salvation. Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is ſpoken of in Scripture, ſometimes in its Cauſe, which is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Righteouſneſs by Faith, and ſometimes in its Effect, which is Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: Therefore I am well pleaſed to ſay with you (to adjust and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that matter right (that the</hi> formalis ratio <hi>of Juſtification is Goſpel Faith and Obedience</hi> (that is, as imputed to us of God for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and taking Juſtification paſſively, meaning as I) <hi>and Pardon of ſin as the neceſſary conſequeent, concomitant, and effect of it. He that will give any other account of it, must</hi> (I believe) <hi>make uſe of ſome other Doctor than St.</hi> Paul.</p>
            <p>One thing more I will note in this Poſtſcript and have done, and that is the particular (<hi>p.</hi> 312.) wherein you ſay you were ready to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe with Mr. <hi>Cole.</hi> You look to your ſelf indeed by ſuch words that you may not lye, but do you think your meaning and Mr. <hi>Coles</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94653:7"/>can indeed ſtand in one Stable? I will therefore expreſs the truth of this ſixth Particular for you with little alteration. <hi>When a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that very Faith and ſincere Goſpel Works which proceed from it is</hi> (you ſay is <hi>not</hi>) <hi>the matter of that Righteouſneſs whereby</hi> (you, to ſave your <hi>Not</hi> before, put in <hi>for which) a ſinner is justified, and ſo intitled to Pardon and Glory: Yet is the Righteouſneſs of Christ alone that for which the Goſpel gives the Believer a right to theſe, and all ſaving bleſſings, who in this reſpect is juſtified through Chriſt, or through his Righteouſneſs, though by Faith:</hi> Faith being indeed the <hi>Matter,</hi> or Material Cauſe; and Gods <hi>Imputing</hi> that Faith (not Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs) to us for Righteouſneſs, the <hi>Form</hi> and Formal Cauſe of our Juſtification.</p>
            <p>Reverend Brother, What will be the iſſue of this preſent endeavour according to my ſmall Ability, I know not: But I will end with this Story. <hi>Luther</hi> one day being with <hi>Melancton, Phillip,</hi> ſays he, I am afraid we are gone too far in that matter of the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> Maſter, ſays <hi>Melancton,</hi> then let us amend and retract it. No, ſays <hi>Luther,</hi> if we do ſo <hi>Phillip,</hi> we ſhall be believed in nothing. Alas! what pity it was, and what prejudice to the <hi>Protestants</hi> Cauſe, that <hi>Luther</hi> had not hearkned to <hi>Melancton?</hi> It muſt be no wonder therefore if you hearken not to me now in my farewell Admonition, which is to chuſe (in this ſmall matter of Difference between us) not to follow <hi>Luther,</hi> but St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> who is ſo much commended by all for his Book of <hi>Retractations.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very reſpectful Brother <hi>JOHN HUMFREY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94653:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Animadverſions ON HIS <hi>End of Diſcord,</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Learned and Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Wrote a Sheet or two in a Letter to Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> upon his <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript to Goſpel Truth</hi> before this later Book called <hi>An End of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> came out. I had no Anſwer to it, nor my Copy back, and therefore I wrote out of my ſoul Papers that Letter over, and ſent it to you to read, and I now ſend you theſe three or four Sheets more upon this new Book, which ſhews the Author a Man ſtill growing in Learning and Induſtry, a Man of Temper and Diſcretion, of prudent Parts and weighty Judgment, as well as excellent in his Faculty of Elocution. I am pleaſed that he gave me a while ago a Viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; but eſpecially for this, that upon his Diſcourſe with me, I came to believe heartily that he is a Man ſincere to God in the Books he writes, and I am glad that I ſo believe, for I know thereby that I love him, becauſe I am glad of it. Nevertheleſs I am not ever the more pleaſed with his new-fangled Invention of ſuch an Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs <hi>in ſe,</hi> as no body ever thought on before, but am diſpleaſed with it, as a needleſs, clutterſome, perplexed, indigeſtible Notion, that does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prave the ſound Doctrine of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and proves at laſt inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant to himſelf. This Book of his I look on, as his <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> fit to be read by Miniſters (ſuch as are of no higher Rank than I) as well as others, as informing and profitable: But it is another work which he had to do, that is, to defend the Truth, and not by ſuch a Doſe to lay it aſleep, and leave it wounded to heal of it ſelf, when no Party is cured. He was ſo well prepared for this work, that I cannot like that he has tyed up his hands by this Book, ſo as in point of ingenuity he could go no further, unleſs ſome body Printed upon him to unlooſe them. It is but a friendly part therefore for me to Print theſe Letters,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94653:8"/>to give him occaſion to deliver himſelf from the double Fetters that are on him, this one on his <hi>Hands,</hi> and the other on his <hi>Judgment</hi> in that perplexed Notion mentioned that muſt be retracted and laid quite aſide if ever he will write clear, worthy himſelf, and profit his Readers.</p>
            <p>Here is this Book call'd by him <hi>An End of Diſcord,</hi> which if Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> had liv'd and joyn'd with him in the Compoſure, might have born ſuch a Title. The Diſcord is between him and the <hi>Independent</hi> Brethren, and how is there an End made of it without the Brethren, or ſome one in their behalf, and with their conſent to agree to it? The Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs <hi>in ſe</hi> is denied by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and the Brethren, ſuppoſing him to be of the ſame Opinion, have been at Diſcord with him about it. Now though he be indeed of Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Judgment, ſo as that in the ſenſe the Brethren hold it, he oppoſes it as much as we, yet in a ſenſe he hath framed by a new Notion of his own, he ſets himſelf on one ſide with the Brethren, as holding an <hi>Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſe,</hi> and me and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> on another. The Queſtion then is, Whether the Brethren approve this Accommodation, and you know (as Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> has ſignified) they are ſo far from it, that it does but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe them the more for the ſhew of his being on their ſide, when he is againſt them. And is this an End of Diſcord? No, no Sir, my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Williams</hi> hath been out, and the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> out, in their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about at firſt to make an Union between <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> by drawing up certain <hi>Theſes</hi> and <hi>Poſitions</hi> in that <hi>latitude</hi> of words as all might ſubſcribe them, and then call that <hi>Union,</hi> when ſuch an Union is no Union, where the <hi>Tongue</hi> is <hi>one,</hi> but the <hi>Mind cloven:</hi> Whereas, if upon a <hi>Toleration</hi> given both from the <hi>State,</hi> they had fallen in with it, by a tolerating one another in <hi>Opinion</hi> (leaving the <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> to any, as they pleaſe, and are able) and united only in <hi>Practice</hi> (according to a Letter of mine to them at the end of my <hi>Middle Way of Juſtification</hi>) they had done their buſineſs, and it is like had never been broken; which ſeeing they are, what ſhould the Brethren do but begin again, and though it be late, yet do ſo now?</p>
            <p>Upon ſuch a bottom as this, the deſign of this Book were abundantly agreeable to my Soul. I am one that would not fall out with any for their Opinion: I think generally they be wiſer than I. I am for Unity for <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> conformiſt and Nonconformiſt, with care againſt the two Rocks of <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> and <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi> As for <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> or the <hi>Five Points,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath made it his buſineſs to bring the Difference to ſo little compaſs, that however the <hi>Synod of Dort</hi> in their day, when <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who had but newly got looſe from <hi>Popery,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94653:8"/>and a part of them from <hi>Lutheraniſm,</hi> were ſo much engaged about it, I could wiſh that thoſe Names of <hi>Calviniſm</hi> and <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> as thoſe of <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibellines,</hi> and our of <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory</hi> were ſunk for ever. Let any of us, or our Brethren, Preach the ſtrongeſt <hi>Calviniſm</hi> we can, and not exceed it, when our <hi>Doctrine</hi> hath been <hi>Calviniſtical,</hi> our <hi>Uſe</hi> muſt be <hi>Arminian,</hi> or we muſt leave Preaching to the People. There is indeed a difference in the <hi>Fifth Point</hi> about <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> wherein the <hi>Synodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> do really differ, and both from St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who will allow that the Regenerate, the Juſtified, the Sanctified may fall away, but never the <hi>Elect.</hi> Now ther are ſome Scriptures to prove that the <hi>Once new born</hi> of God cannot finally fall away, which the <hi>Arminians</hi> cannot anſwer, and ſome Scriptures to argue that they may, as the <hi>Calviniſt</hi> cannot anſwer, which makes it fit and equal that neither of them ſhould be ſo fierce, but give leave to one another to make the good uſe (and not the bad) of their own Opinions. The Controverſie as to the other Five Points, will come all to this Diſpute only, Whether the <hi>Grace</hi> of God be <hi>Reſiſtible</hi> (as they have expreſſed it), and when the <hi>Will</hi> cannot be compelled or forced, ſo that it hath, and muſt have a power to reſiſt, it appears hard to ſay it is <hi>irreſiſtible.</hi> My Opinion is this, that though it is true, that Man hath a <hi>Natural</hi> power ſtill to reſiſt, yet when Electing or Effectual Grace once comes, it takes away the <hi>Moral</hi> power of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and upon that account it may be called irreſiſtible. As the <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate</hi> hath a <hi>Natural</hi> power (or his faculties) to <hi>believe, repent,</hi> and ſo may be ſaved if he will: Yet having ſuch an indiſpoſition (which is his <hi>Moral Impotency</hi>) thereunto as he has, he never will, and becauſe he will not, he is damned: So the <hi>Elect</hi> hath his <hi>Natural</hi> power to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt</hi> if he will, but the Grace of God does ſo diſpoſe him, as that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> he cannot, and therefore he will not, and ſo by Grace he is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. As for the <hi>Arminian,</hi> they plead for Grace to prevent us, to aſſiſt us, to co-operate with us as much as we, and that we can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without it in order to be ſaved. Neither may their contending that all may be ſaved if they will, offend any of us, at leaſt that hold Univerſal Redemption; for this is true, that whoſoever will, <hi>may?</hi> Only we do add, that when any <hi>will,</hi> that is yet farther of <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid this according to Charity, a little ſurpaſſing this Author, I think fit to take notice of one Chapter in this Book that concerns me. It is the <hi>Eighth,</hi> but in order to it I find in the ſeventh theſe two Queſtions raiſed, to wit, How our ſins were imputed to Chriſt as to his Satisfaction, and how his Righteouſneſs is imputed to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94653:9"/>us in our Juſtification. The difference in Opinion herein does ſpring (he tells us) from the diverſe conceptions we have of Chriſts <hi>Sureti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> whereof we have mention but once in Scripture, and I will ſay but this little about it! That, there in nothing oftentimes, ſo much hinders the right underſtanding of a Text of Scripture, or words of an Author, as the apprehenſion that there is ſome more profoundneſs in it than there is: And ſo it is here as to this word <hi>Surety,</hi> whereof I am perſwaded there is nothing to be underſtood by it, but Chriſts Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding as Mediator in our behalf, and undertaking the doing that in regard to his Prieſthood (of which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is ſpeaking in the place) as was neceſſary to the reconciling God to us, ſo as to be willing to make and as h might in Juſtice make, that Covenant, or grant the Conditions of the Goſpel to us. As for Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and others telling us farther things of this Suretiſhip, to wit, of Chriſts engaging on <hi>Gods part</hi> that he ſhall perform what he promiſes, and on <hi>our part,</hi> that the Elect ſhall perform the Condition, it is <hi>Gratis</hi> diſcourſe; for on Gods part he needs no ſuch Surety, and as for us, the Covenant is univerſal; and if Chriſt was a Surety in a proper ſenſe for our performance, then ſhould all perform it, and be ſaved. Let us conceive therefore of nothing intended by this word <hi>Surety,</hi> for Chriſt to do, but what is neceſſary to Gods <hi>making,</hi> not his, or our <hi>keeping,</hi> this Covenant, and let who will make the moſt of it. I come to the firſt Queſtion, How our ſins were imputed to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 73. Having told us what on one ſide we think, wherein I wiſh he could have cited Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to explain it, for his mind is ſo over full of his Notion, as he is not fit to do it for us. <hi>The other ſide</hi> (ſays he) <hi>think Chriſt came into the ſame bond as a Pecuniary Surety with us, or was our Repreſent alive in ſuch a ſenſe as that we are Legally esteemed to do or ſuffer what he did:</hi> This Opinion of the Brethren Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> thought ſo dangerous, that he ſet himſelf againſt it, Book after Book, as that which does argumentatively bring in <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> and according to his frequent words, <hi>ſubvert the Goſpel.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> is ſo ſugard here, ſo gracious, ſo mealy, as to tell them, that <hi>this would be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous indeed, if they did not renounce all aſſuming boaſts as if they were as righteous as Chriſt, or ſtood on terms with God, needing no more acts of Mercy than that one, of appointing Chriſt to be their Mediator.</hi> But what if they be all ſo humble (as I believe they are) as none of them to have ſuch <hi>boasting,</hi> yet ſo long as that Tenent does argumentatively in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch conſequences as this, and no leſs indeed than this, (wherein Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſhews his ſtrength) how can he daub thus with ſuch untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Mortar as he here makes? As if the <hi>Opinion,</hi> as well as the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94653:9"/>
               <hi>Brother</hi> that holds it, was to be own'd. And how many the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of this Doctrine, does Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſhew in his Books?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 75, 76. The <hi>Brethren</hi> ſuppoſing (as before) that we obeyed and ſuffered in Chriſt do ground it (he counts here) upon <hi>Adams</hi> being a figure of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the 5th of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and he is informing them, that we muſt not ſay that we <hi>obey</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as we are ſaid to have <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> in <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe we were all in <hi>Adam</hi> as our Root; but none of us, not the <hi>Elect,</hi> not the <hi>Believer,</hi> ſo in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as in <hi>him,</hi> which he has ſome where elſe alſo; I cannot turn to the place, but having ſpent ſome thoughts hereupon without Book, I will ſet my ſelf to ſet them down. What <hi>Chriſt</hi> did for us in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> he did for <hi>Mankind,</hi> but all Mankind are not in him as we were in <hi>Adam,</hi> that is certain, tho' Redemption be univerſal. The Believer only is his <hi>Seed,</hi> who is not thus neither, that is <hi>ſeminally</hi> in him. Beſides that, if the Believer or the Elect be accounted of God to have done what Chriſt did, he muſt be accounted of God to have fulfilled the Law in him, and ſo to have nothing to do himſelf for his Salvation, which is to leap into the Gulph of <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> which we avoid. This Notion now is not any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar one of Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> but what others alſo inſiſt upon, yet am not I contented with it. I do not ſee how we can be ſaid to <hi>ſin in Adam</hi> (the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text does not prove it) upon this account of Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> that we was in his <hi>Loins.</hi> If you prove it by that Text, which ſays, <hi>Levi</hi> paid Tythes to <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> in <hi>Abraham,</hi> I prove the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary by another, where it is ſaid of the Children unborn, that they had <hi>neither done any good ar evil.</hi> One of theſe Texts is certainly as argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative, as the other. We may be ſaid to eat of the Tree, and to dreſs the Garden, and to do all that ever <hi>Adam</hi> did <hi>Phyſically,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his <hi>Loins,</hi> but we did not <hi>ſin</hi> in him, which is a <hi>Moral</hi> evil. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal corruption is ſin, but not his, or this ſin. There is no ſuch ſin or Moral good without the Will. <hi>Actus non facit reum, niſi mens ſit rea,</hi> and in this ſenſe that Axiom, <hi>Actiones</hi> (as to good and evil) <hi>ſunt ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorum</hi> is undeniable. What then ſhall we ſay to this Chapter, which tells us, that by <hi>Adams diſobedience we were made ſinners, and by Chriſts obedience made righteous,</hi> and the like? I anſwer to ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns our purpoſe, that I have pitcht on this Solution in my <hi>Ultima Manus</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 6.) where ſtanding to our Principles, I affirm, That this Imputation which is ſuppoſed here on both ſides, as to <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, and <hi>Chriſts</hi> obedience, is to be underſtood only in regard to the <hi>Effects.</hi> We are made ſinners in <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, in regard to the fruit of it, for we all <hi>dye</hi> by reaſon of it: So we are made righteous by <hi>Chriſts</hi> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in regard to the benefits of it, as Juſtification, and ſo Pardon and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94653:10"/>Salvation, which we have by it upon believing. We are not <hi>Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter</hi> righteous by <hi>Chriſts</hi> obedience (this we carefully deny), nor <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliter</hi> ſinners by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin: But <hi>Effective</hi> we are ſo, in regard to the fruit, or <hi>quoad Effectus</hi> as to both. This is a ſolid determination, and which I ſtand to: See the place in that Book. It may be objected, If this be ſo, here is a difficulty ariſes, We are puniſhed, and that with Death for the ſin of another, how can that be juſt? And if God may puniſh us with Temporal Death for <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, he may with Eternal. I anſwer therefore. That though <hi>Death</hi> inflicted on <hi>Adam</hi> for his ſin, was indeed a puniſhment on him; yet is Death in it ſelf no puniſhment on us. <hi>Adam</hi> was made of the Earth Mortal as we, but he was put into the Garden where was the Tree of Life, whereof, ſo long as he might eat, it would ſave his Life; but upon his ſin, God excluded him from it, and having not the Free to eat on, when his time came, he muſt needs dye. The Sentence of Death was in effect executed on him in excluding him <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> But as for us we never had the Tree to eat on, and cannot be puniſhed by the excluſion from what we never had, but according to Nature, we being Mortal, and of courſe appointed to dye, our Death, as Natural, is neither good nor evil in it ſelf, but in regard to what follows it, that is the reward to come, according as out Lives have been in the World, and if good, it is but a Gate to Bleſſedneſs. After this you may ask, What think you then of the more common Doctrine, that it is not as we were in <hi>Adams Loins,</hi> but as we were in <hi>Adams Covenant</hi> that we <hi>ſinned in him,</hi> and ſo were liable to the ſame puniſhment? I anſwer; beſides that, it can never be proved, that thoſe words, <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof;</hi> was ſaid to you or I, when they were ſaid to <hi>Adam;</hi> this Aſſertion is too grievous for my embrace, becauſe it makes the Conſtitution only of God, that is his Will alone, without any of the ſinner, to be the cauſe of Mans damnation. I will yet not leave, but ſeeing I am fallen on the Point, I will conſider what <hi>Original Sin</hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is that I own. There are three things according to the common Doctrine wherein original Sin conſiſts the Want of Original Righteouſneſs, <hi>Adams</hi> firſt guilt, and the Corruption of our Nature, from whence Actual Tranſgreſſions proceed. For the ſecond I have ſpoke to For the <hi>firſt,</hi> The Schools have conceived that <hi>Adam</hi> was Endowed with a <hi>ſupernatural Grace,</hi> beſides his Natural Righteous Conſtitution, which by his <hi>Fall</hi> he loſt, and ſo we, but our <hi>naturals</hi> and <hi>Free-will</hi> remains. Now I believe no ſuch thing, as that <hi>Adam</hi> had any Righteouſneſs or Grace <hi>ſupernatural,</hi> but only Nature entire; for Grace is indeed a Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal thing, or Auxiliatory for fallen Nature, which <hi>Adam</hi> needed not,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94653:10"/>and there can be no loſs of that which never was. If by Original Righteouſneſs, the integrity of <hi>Adams</hi> Nature be meant only, the want or loſs of this is included in the third. As for which I believe that <hi>Adam</hi> falling, depraved his Nature, and being depraved himſelf he begets Children with this Corruption in their Nature, The <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> is infected with ignorance and diſobedience, the <hi>Ataxy</hi> in his Faculties upon his Fall, is begotten in ours, and ſo I hold Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin according to the <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which ſpeaks of this, and nothing elſe, though I did not therefore ſo take it up. <hi>Omnes peccaverunt,</hi> id eſt, <hi>in omnes propagatum eſt malum, quod est peccatum</hi> (ſays <hi>Melancthon</hi>) and ſo we are by Nature <hi>filii ira,</hi> not upon <hi>Adams,</hi> but our own account. This, or thus much I hold with the <hi>Church</hi> againſt <hi>Pelagius;</hi> ſo that there is a neceſſity therefore of <hi>Grace</hi> in order to Salvation: But whether of <hi>ſpecial</hi> Grace againſt <hi>Arminius</hi> alſo, which I have hitherto imbibed, I leave others to their own Sentiments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 77. Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and I do hold that Chriſts Obligation to bear our puniſhment was a ſingle Obligation, or an Obligation of his own, not our Obligation, though our puniſhment. Our Obligation is <hi>ex delicto,</hi> his ex voluntario contractu, ſo that he ſuffered not as a Sinner: But the Brethren think otherwiſe, <hi>That our ſins were ſo imputed to Chriſt, as to give him the denomination and judicial acceptation of a Sinner in the esteem of God and the Law.</hi> This being ſo, what ſays Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> to it, to end the Diſcord? Why, <hi>Notwithstanding this, ſo long as they deny that Chriſt bad any defilement in him, or any ſin of his own, only our ſins imputed to him, and he was but a Legal Sinner; this difference cannot justifie mutual Cenſure.</hi> What? And can it not indeed? Then I promiſe you we muſt be more friendly to the <hi>Antinomian</hi> alſo; for it is very abuſive for any to think that ſuch a one as Dr. <hi>Criſps</hi> or any <hi>Univerſity Graduate,</hi> did ever believe that the <hi>Accident</hi> of one <hi>Subject</hi> could migrate into another, ſo that we are to take their words how broad ſoever (as when they account Chriſt took on him the fault, as well as the puniſhment, to wit, our faults, and only <hi>Legally</hi>) in the ſenſe of thoſe Orthodox Divines as have commonly ſaid he ſuffered as a Sinner, and <hi>Luther,</hi> as the greateſt Sinner: Yet are ſuch ſayings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, by, and according to us, who deny that he was our <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> though a <hi>Days-man</hi> betwixt God and us, he bore our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we might not bear it. An Opinion may be of ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and he that holds it not ſee it; and a Man may hold a Tenent in the <hi>Theory,</hi> which he does not in the <hi>Practice,</hi> but live as free from thoſe ill conſequences as he that holds the contrary Opinion. In ſuch
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94653:11"/>a caſe ſuch a <hi>Brother</hi> is not to be cenſured, but born with, but the <hi>Opinion</hi> the Tenent is to be cenſured and refuted, and ſuch Cenſure to be juſtified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 80, 81. The Apology he makes there for our Opinion (that is his, I mean, and mine and Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi>) againſt the common Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants is ſo well, handſome, humble, true, clear and taking, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but commend it, <hi>Ut nihil ſupra.</hi> The following Pages are as ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, in clearing us from <hi>Popery. I thank him for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 84. He ſpeaks of the Manner of Imputation of Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and tells us the double ſenſe thereof; on the one ſide, the ſenſe of the Brethren, which is the ſame (that God reckons us to have Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally done and ſuffered what Chriſt did) as before, but in more words: And on the other ſide our ſenſe, which he might diſpatch in two words, <hi>Quoad Effectus,</hi> but he clouds it ſo with his Notion of <hi>Gods adjudging that the Obedience and Sufferings of Chriſt is our Pleadable Security</hi> for his benefits purchaſed, that I cannot tell what to make of it. For what an idle impertinent thing is this to talk of Gods adjudging Chriſts Obedience to be <hi>our Pleadable Security</hi> for the enjoyment of that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he does adjudge us upon the account hereof to the <hi>very enjoyment!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 86. <hi>By this you ſee</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that we riſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot ſo high, as to ſay we are accounted to do or ſuffer what Chriſt did, and ſo to be abſolved imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the Sentence of the Law of Works: Nor fall ſo low as a meer participation of the Effects of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, but aſſent to an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs it ſelf relatively to thoſe Effects.</hi> Alas for Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> Into what ſhifts for want of an Ingenuous confeſſion is he brought? Do not I and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſay this? Is this indeed a <hi>Middle</hi> Way in good earneſt? Have not we ſaid the ſame before him? And is not Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſetled Judgment, and which he maintains as well as I and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> that <hi>Legally</hi> (which our former Divines have ſtill ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not imputed to us: and when he ſays <hi>Relatively</hi> (after us) in regard to the Effects, is not this it which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and I ſay, when we affirm againſt the common Doctrine, that Chriſts Righteouſneſs is imputed not <hi>in ſe,</hi> but only <hi>in the Effects?</hi> You ſee it more fully in my Letter to his <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi> Alas! what a little Self-denyal here would have ſerved him, to make the Acknowledgment, of taking this from us, and of his Agreement with it! And is this the <hi>Meant</hi> between <hi>them</hi> that <hi>riſe too high,</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> that <hi>fall too low,</hi> when it is the very ſame we ſay, and he takes it from us? The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction onely excepted, for when the <hi>in ſe,</hi> and the <hi>Effects</hi> are Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he will have Chriſts Righteouſneſs ours <hi>in its ſelf,</hi> upon our ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is <hi>Relatively</hi> ours in regard to the Effects.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94653:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I come to the Chapter that concerns me, the Title whereof is this <hi>An Attempt to accommodate the Difference between ſuch as judge Chriſts Righteouſneſs is imputed only in the Effects, and not</hi> in ſe, <hi>and thoſe of us who think it is imputed</hi> in ſe. Theſe words <hi>[and thoſe of us]</hi> I take all from Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> This is that Mr. <hi>Lobb</hi> (if we may believe his Books) and I think Mr. <hi>Chancy</hi> took ſo ill from him, as to write ſo engagedly againſt him, that he pretends to hold with the <hi>Brethren</hi> in maintaining the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs <hi>in ſe</hi> againſt thoſe that deny it, that is ſuch as I, Mr. <hi>Baxter, Wotton, Forbs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> names <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, Grotius</hi>) when yet he is fundamentally of our Opinion, and ſo far as concerns the <hi>Brethren,</hi> nothing at all for them. If he be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at my ſaying that he agrees with us (excepting his new Notion, which ſignifies not) I can't help it, for I can ſay no otherwiſe, and methinks that which is ſaid but now ſhould make him aſhamed of it. You ſee there, no <hi>Middle way</hi> for him.</p>
            <p>The Brethren and common Proteſtant do underſtand that Chriſt in his dying for us, did ſuffer in our ſtead, which can bear no other true ſenſe in their Judgment but this, that he was our Repreſentative, ſo as what he did and ſuffered in our behalf, is in Law-ſenſe accounted of God as done and ſuffered by us; ſo that his Satisfaction and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereupon, is <hi>Legally</hi> (I ſay) or in the acceptation of <hi>Law</hi> reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him as our Righteouſneſs; for being received by Faith, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ours, ſo as that it does formally juſtifie us. Here is moſt fairly that which hath been, and is to be underſtood by an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> to wit, ſuch as our former <hi>Proteſtants</hi> accounted <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally held: But Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (letting theſe Brethren know in the way, that when we grant againſt the <hi>Socinian,</hi> that Chriſt died <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> by which we mean that he dyed to ſave us from dying, who muſt elſe have dyed our ſelves, we do not underſtand as they, that <hi>we dyed and ſuffered in him,</hi> for to dye in our room, that we might not dye, and to be accounted of God to have dyed, or dyed in him, is an inconſiſtency that may convince them) that Reverend Man, and faithful Servant of Chriſt being ſenſible how this Doctrine does argumentatively lead to <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> and did hurry ſo many of this Nation into it, as it did, before he wrote, he, being ſtirred up, we may believe, by God as an Inſtrument to eradicate the <hi>Antinomian Hereſie,</hi> did ſet himſelf, with aſſiſtance, in many Books to refute this Opinion, as neceſſary to that end.</p>
            <p>Upon this true and ſhort account given, I ask then, Is Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> in good earneſt now of the Judgment of the <hi>Brethren,</hi> or of Mr. <hi>Baxters?</hi> He knows in his Conſcience, and we all ſee by this Book, and all his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94653:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>others, a manifeſt confirmation every, where with great ſtrength and weight, and diligent reading (which may ſhame thoſe that deſpiſe him as not Learned) of the Doctrine taught by that profound Divine, and moſt ſincere Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt. And ſhall this <hi>Eliſha</hi> that hath ſtill followed his <hi>Elijah</hi> go now in Words (for it is no more) to caſt away his <hi>Mantle,</hi> and diſown his Maſter? I cannot endure that when Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> makes here two ſides, he ſhould rank the <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>He</hi> on the one ſide, and <hi>I</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> on the other. If any other had wrote the Title to this Chapter, I would have ſaid it is falſe, Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and I, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> are of one Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 104. <hi>There are ſome that ſay, the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted</hi> in ſe <hi>for Juſtification; and ſome that ſay it is not imputed</hi> in ſe, <hi>but</hi> quoad Effectus. He numbers himſelf among the former. Of the former then, there are belike two ſorts with him, ſuch as think the <hi>Elect</hi> or <hi>Believer</hi> to be accounted by God to have obliged and ſuffered in Chriſt, which he diſproves, and therefore tells of another ſort, that is, ſuch as do not think that God does judicially account any to have obeyed and ſuffered in Chriſt (for that he ſtoutly denies in all his Books, as well as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and I) and yet do hold an Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs <hi>in ſe,</hi> which indeed is a Rarity, for I believe there is not any but himſelf, and it is fit therefore to hear how Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſingle ſelf does hold this (even in oppoſition to the Brethren, as well as us) but that I have already canvaſed that new perplexed Contrivance (which he invented for the ſake of thoſe tender Brethren that cannot bear with the ſound Doctrine of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> though there is none of them I believe that regard the Invention) in my <hi>Pacification,</hi> my <hi>Appendix</hi> to him at large in the End of my <hi>Ultima Manus,</hi> and alſo in my Letter before to his Poſtſcript; ſo that there is nothing left more to do, but to wonder at this Reverend Man, what he means thus to perſiſt, eſpecially in telling us of <hi>a variety among this ſort in wording their Conceptions, but they all come to one,</hi> which indeed is well ſaid, for he alone in the one, and only one that ever entertained ſuch an Imagination. Well, what then is this that one ſenſe it comes to? Why this, that <hi>God according to the Covenant of Redemption where he promiſes to Chriſt to ſave the Believer, he judicially accounts what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered to be his pleadable Security. This we take to be Imputation.</hi> We! what we? None ſurely but himſelf. he dare not ſay, as they muſt, who indeed hold an Imputation <hi>in ſe,</hi> that God does judicially account what <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath done and ſuffered to be <hi>Legally</hi> the Believers (this is the Doctrine of an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> which he militates againſt in all his Books, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in all his) but to be <hi>his pleadable ſecurity.</hi> And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94653:12"/>what is that? Is that <hi>Juſtification?</hi> Is that I ſay again an Imputation of what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered to the Believer ſo as to be that Righteouſneſs <hi>in ſe,</hi> whereby he is juſtified? No, what Imputation then <hi>in ſe</hi> is it? Did he that wrote the reſt of the Book write this? Did he write it when he was awake, or aſleep? If he was a wake, let him tell what. That the Performance of the Covenant of Redemption by Chriſt does afford us a pleadable ſecurity, that if we believe we ſhall be ſaved, there is no body queſtions. That this pleadable ſecurity is an Effect and Benefit of that performance, is not to be queſtioned neither. That the Imputation then of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to us for this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Security (if there be any ſuch Imputation) is an Imputation of it only in the <hi>Effects.</hi> (or <hi>quoad Effectus</hi>) and not <hi>in ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> I have it already in my former Letter: That this pleadable Security ariſes from the promiſe of the Goſpel Covenant, as well as from that to Chriſt in the Covenant of Redemption Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſays: And if from the Goſpel there ariſes no Imputation of Chriſts Obedience to us <hi>in ſe,</hi> how does it from the Law of Mediation? That God does impute Chriſts Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance to us for Righteouſneſs is ſaid by Divines; but I ſay again, where is it ſaid in Scripture, or by any Divine of Note, that he imputes it to us for our pleadable Security, only by himſelf? it is true, that we may impute or apply it to our ſelves ſo; but where, or by whom is it ſaid that <hi>God</hi> ſo <hi>imputes it,</hi> and <hi>judicially</hi> ſo imputes it? Is this the work of Judgment? And why does our otherwiſe very worthy Brother take upon him by making ſuch Speeches for God as he does, to put him upon the ſaying any thing more than needs? What needs ſuch a Speech: Thou believer, I judicially eſteem and pronounce thee to be one that I promiſed to my Son in the Covenant of Redemption to ſave in reward to his performance of that Covenant, therefore I judicially alſo account what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered to be thy pleadable Security, that thou ſhalt be ſaved? Is it not enough that God ſays this? Thou ſinner being one that haft believed, and repented, and ſo performed (through my Grace) the Covenant of the Goſpel, I do therefore according to my promiſe therein to thy ſelf and all Mankind judicially ſentence thee to Life everlaſting. Let the Believer have this Sentence pronounced by the <hi>Covenant of the Goſpel</hi> he will not need, and ſcarce over thought of any other by the <hi>Covenant of Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 107. As for thoſe that ſay Chriſts Righteouſneſs is not imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> but in the <hi>Effects</hi> they oppoſe all this (ſays he) but they great the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to be the meritorious Cauſe of our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: they narrow not their Opinion to a procuring only a Covenant of Grace or Law of the Goſpel, but ſay Chriſt purchaſed the Benefits
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94653:13"/>firſt which that Covenant beſtows: they are ſound in the Doctrine of Satisfaction: they abhor the preſenting our Faith or Evangelical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God as any Satisfaction to Juſtice, Attonement for Sin, or Prince of Salvation. Upon theſe Accounts more at large expreſſed bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by him, a forbearance is very charitably and commendably pleaded for theſe Brethren by this good Brother, in their behalf, who no doubt is well inclined to it himſelf, for this is certainly a very ingenious kind of <hi>Apologizing</hi> for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, and <hi>Mine,</hi> and his <hi>Own</hi> Opinion. Nevertheleſs I have two or three things to take Notice of further in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>One is, <hi>P.</hi> 109. Our Opinion <hi>quoad Effectus,</hi> he ſays does amount to an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> becauſe the Divine Mind muſt apply the Merits of Chriſt to our Faith to make it a Righteouſneſs. But how ſo? Why if ſo, the Divine Mind he counts muſt apply his Righteouſneſs to our perſons. If through Chriſts Merits our Faith is made a Righteouſneſs, then his Merits muſt make our perſons Righteous. This is his ſenſe, which he hath in diverſe expreſſions three times in the Paragraph. Very well now I ſay, that if through Chriſts Merits God does impute our Faith for Righteouſneſs, then muſt the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs be an Imputation only <hi>quoad, Effectus,</hi> for this is a grand Effect of it, that our Faith, which of it ſelf is none, is through thoſe Merits imputed for Righteouſneſs. And if the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt be Imputed only <hi>quoad Effectus,</hi> it is not <hi>Imputed in ſe</hi> for our Juſtification. The Divine Mind (ſays he) does apply Chriſts Righteouſneſs to the Perſon, which in plain words is, God does Impute it to a Perſon: But what Imputation is it! is it not an <hi>Imputation quoad Effectus?</hi> It is doubtleſs, for that Effect which Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs has to make our Faith a Righteouſneſs, it hath the ſame to make the Perſon accepted as a Goſpel Righteous Perſon, and for his ſake to be dealt with accordingly, but not as a Legally Righteous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as Chriſt is. It is thus, and no otherwiſe, whereas he ſpeaks of it as if it were an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> which our <hi>Opinion</hi> (he ſays) <hi>amounts</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nay <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> and <hi>infers</hi> (he ſays) <hi>as Neceſſary:</hi> But if it were an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in ſe,</hi> then ſhould Chriſts <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> (not our <hi>Faith</hi>) be imputed to us for Righteouſneſs, which falls in (he knows) with the Opinion of the Brethren, and makes it the Formal Cauſe of our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Alas that this perplexing Notion ſhould lead this conſidering Brother into thoſe Blunderings, which ſeeing it does, I do write this Book on purpoſe to proſecute it (if I can) to the death, not to hurt him, but to rid him of it. That what he ſays is very handſome for perſwading the contrary minded to bear with (if not receive) our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94653:13"/>becauſe it hath all the Conveniency as to the Subſtantial Doctrine of the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> which the <hi>Brethren</hi> can make of theirs: Yet he is ſhort in his diſcernment of that very Critical Point, wherein the hinge of this Controverſie among us does turn, which is, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether the Righteouſneſs <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>of Faith,</hi> be the <hi>Formal</hi> Righteouſneſs that juſtifies us. I wonder that this very ſearching and judicious Brother ſhould not ſee here his Defect. An imputed Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs <hi>in ſe</hi> makes Chriſts Righteouſneſs the <hi>Formal Cauſe:</hi> an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs only <hi>quoad Effectus</hi> makes his Righteouſneſs the <hi>Meritorious Cauſe</hi> alone of our <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another is <hi>P.</hi> 11. <hi>I could wiſh a very worthy Perſon of this Opinion, would review in his own account of Juſtification, where he faith it is that act whereby God imputes to every ſound believer his Faith for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon the account of Chriſts Satisfaction and Merits, and gives Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Life as the benefits of it.</hi> I cannot but deſire to know this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſeeing as theſe words render him, he ſhould be living, for what this Author ſays is ſo agreeable to my Mind, that if it were not, but that I know the Commendation he gives him is not belonging to me, I ſhould have thought they were my own Words. The following Saying he cites accordingly, <hi>Though Christs Sacrifice the Defects of Faith which is our Righteouſneſs, are pardoned, and by his Merits that imperfect Duty is accounted or imputed to us for Righteouſneſs, which it is not in its ſelf.</hi> Both I think exceeding well. But Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> objects, <hi>How can Pardon be the effect of imputing Faith for Righteouſneſs (which is Juſtification) and yet God cannot impute faith for Righteouſneſs, unleſs he first pardon its defects for the ſake of Christs Sacrifice?</hi> This Objection I foreſaw, and have prevented (That he adds beſides is ſtumbling at a Straw, and ought not to retard us) in my Book of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 24.) where having defined Juſtification after this ſame manner, I, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m the concluding my Explication thereof have theſe words. <hi>After this I diſtinguiſh this pardoning, and bearing with the defects of our Faith, Repentance, New Obedience, which are Conditions of the Goſpel Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſo our Goſpel Righteouſneſs, or that which is imputed for Righteouſneſs: And that General or Total Pardon which the Covenant promiſes, and becomes abſolute upon performing the Condition. The one of theſe is that very Grace, or Act of Grace it ſelf that goes into that Act of Imputation, or Act that imputes our Faith for Righteouſneſs, when the other, I ſay ſtill, is the Effect or Benefit following Juſtification.</hi> I will add, The <hi>one</hi> let us note farther is diſpenſed by God as <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> or <hi>Abſolute Lord</hi> (ſo I apprehend), and is more or leſs to one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than another at his will and pleaſure, that hath no bounds to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94653:14"/>ſet to it: When the <hi>other</hi> is diſpenſed by him as <hi>Rector</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> to every Man alike upon the performed Condition. I will yet add, And this may give ſome more Line to the Aſſertors of <hi>Free-Grace</hi> than they every yet thought on for <hi>Improvement,</hi> and that ſolid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort I raiſe from hence in my <hi>Pacification, p.</hi> 27, 28, 29. quoted again in my <hi>Righteouſneſs of God, p.</hi> 21. (in the Margin) which I commend to the Reader as my <hi>Bleſſing</hi> while alive and dead.</p>
            <p>The lat is p. 112. The reaſon for our denial of an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> he renders truly (as the chief reaſon) to be <hi>an apprehenſion that there is no ſuch Imputation, unleſs we are accounted of God to have done and ſuffered what Chriſt did, which would induce the</hi> Antinomian <hi>Scheme.</hi> This is ſo, it is the reaſon, and that the meaning and intent of that phraſe is no other than this, I know no body like to deny unleſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>But that I deny</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to be the only import of that phraſe; for when that Righteouſneſs it ſelf is imputed Relatively to the ſpecial Effects of it, it is truly an Imputation in ſe.</hi> Here is a double deceit, errour, or falſhood. One in the <hi>Logick</hi> of it, the other in the <hi>matter</hi> of it. In the <hi>Logick</hi> the words <hi>[it ſelf]</hi> muſt not be put in, we deny an Imputation of this Righteouſneſs <hi>it ſelf</hi> (or in it ſelf.) This <hi>it ſelf</hi> therefore is a <hi>Petitio Principis,</hi> that is fallacious, which muſt be left out, and then as to the <hi>matter,</hi> I ſay, an affirming Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to be imputed (that is reckoned or made ours) <hi>Relatively</hi> only in regard to the <hi>Effects,</hi> is the denyal of it to be ſo <hi>in ſe,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the received ſenſe of that Diſtinction. But indeed if we might coyn here a new Diſtinction between Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and I, and not do hurt by it, making an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> to be either a <hi>Legal,</hi> or <hi>Relative</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation only: So long as Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> does maintain that Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is not imputed <hi>in ſe</hi> Legally to a Believer, and ſtands on the Negative againſt the Brethren herein as much as I: If I grant to him this <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> which is <hi>Relative</hi> only, I ſee not but he and I are perfectly agreed, and ſo all the new-fangled Notion of another Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſts <hi>Right</hi> to us in it ſelf, or of his <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Mediatorial Law, <hi>for our pleadable Security,</hi> inſtead of <hi>for our Righteouſneſs</hi> (that is, inſtead of an Imputation <hi>in ſe,</hi> an Imputation only <hi>quoad hunc effectum,</hi> an open prevarication) which will never be made to ſignifie any thing, may be ſpared, and that clutter be quite over. But I cannot in conſcience grant him the uſe of an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> according to this ſenſe, becauſe an <hi>Imputation quoad Effectus</hi> is underſtood to be <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum dividens,</hi> and conſequently contrary to an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our common underſtanding of that diſtinction. Beſides that, the uſe of the term <hi>in ſe,</hi> in ſuch a latitude, may be dangerous to many, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94653:14"/>the untrue uſe of it ſo long by him, has done (as I doubt) too much hurt already. I cannot therefore but be a little more ſevere herein, and muſt obſerve, that when Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> does deny the Brethrens ſenſe to be the only import of the phraſe, <hi>in ſe,</hi> he denys it upon the account of the term <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively,</hi> which term he took from me (I am confident) and had no thoughts of it, or ſuch a meaning or evaſion when he at firſt ſaid, that <hi>Beſides the Effects the very Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is imputed to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever.</hi> Now when I, or Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (from which of us he takes it) uſe the <hi>Term</hi> in contradiſtinction to that <hi>in ſe,</hi> while we explain our Opinion thus purpoſely, that the Effects are ours <hi>Really,</hi> but Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ours only in <hi>regard</hi> to theſe Effects, and Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> takes the term from me, without telling that, but propoſing it as his own, does come ſo long after in his <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> and <hi>this</hi> Book to give us this account of that Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his as aforeſaid, and telling us, that if the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be imputed to us <hi>in the Effects,</hi> then it muſt be <hi>it ſelf Relatively ours</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to them, I cannot ſee how any one can count that there is either ſatisfaction or ingenuity in it. For when this word <hi>[it ſelf]</hi> is (I ſay) ſophiſtical, and muſt not be taken for <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> as if we were proprietors of that Righteouſneſs whereof Chriſt only is the proprietor, but of the benefit he hath procured us by it, which is the perfect ſenſe and truth, and all the truth which in good earneſt it contains, Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> methinks ſhould not be ſo ſhameleſs as any longer to perſiſt. If he had ſaid this at firſt, if indeed he had had this, and no other meaning, but this of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative</hi> at firſt, then could not I, or any of Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Friends, have been offended, as if he had departed from us in this bottom Point of difference between the common Proteſtant and us in the matter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. Nor could he have been offended at the <hi>Brethren,</hi> as if they wrong'd him, by ſaying he agreed with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in this Poſition, that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not imputed to the Believer <hi>in ſe,</hi> but <hi>in the Effects;</hi> for in the true ſenſe of the Poſition Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> as well as I, agrees with Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> But ſeeing he ſaid not, nor thought any ſuch thing at firſt, (for he could not have ſaid <hi>Beſides the Effects,</hi> if he had meant <hi>quoad Effectus</hi>) but ſays this now, I can ſay no leſs, but that if another had ſaid ſo, it is falſe, abſurd, a piece of Plagiariſm, which is bold-fac'd, diſingenious, not fit for any man to have ſaid that has been Univerſity bread. I remember one Axiom I learned there, <hi>Membra di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntia ſunt contraria,</hi> (for <hi>contraria ſunt vel in Dividendo, vol in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerendo</hi>) which infers, that if a Diſputant affirms a thing of one branch of a Diſtinction, and is brought to the allowing or affirming the ſame of the other (as Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> here is reduc'd) the man is brought to a ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, and ſo <hi>Non-pluſt.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> therefore ſet up his Staff
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94653:15"/>here, and come to a plain Determination. If the Brethren be right in their <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> let him take it in their ſenſe, and cleave to them: If Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> be right <hi>quoad Effectus,</hi> then let him follow us. If he will follow neither, he muſt halt by himſelf.</p>
            <p>The laſt Chapter of Mr. <hi>Ws. is an Abſtract</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>of what helpt him to avoid ſome perplexities</hi> (when there as no need of ſuch, unleſs he had made them) <hi>concerning Juſtification:</hi> Which <hi>Abſtract</hi> in fine comes to this, that he takes <hi>the Rule of Judgment to be the Goſpel Law in a ſubordinate connexion with the Law of Mediation,</hi> which makes the Juſtification of a Believer to be equivalent to a twofold Juſtification, but he <hi>hopes</hi> (notwithſtanding his talk of a double Bar in his <hi>Postſcript) that none would think that he ſaid there is a twofold Justification:</hi> For the <hi>Sentence</hi> is but <hi>one</hi> (he ſays) though equivalent to a <hi>twofold</hi> Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. This is very dainty, I muſt needs ſay, but I intend not any Critical Examination of the Matter; Only I think I can tell what is that hath helpt Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> into his perplexities better than he can tell what will help him out. It is this that he hath brought himſelf into the belief of ſome real truth in his Notion as will bear him out to ſpeak as the Brethren, and ſo avoid (as he accounts) the <hi>offending the weak,</hi> and yet hold ſtill with Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> And it is no wonder if this brings him into his perplexity, when all his new-fangled Conceptions do ſerve only to put him upon freſh abſurdities, and encreaſe it. He is come now to let his thoughts run upon fancying a double Rule of Judgment com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing both the Law of <hi>Mediation,</hi> as well as the Law of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> The <hi>Law of Mediaion</hi> was a Law we know that Chriſt alone was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and though a Law may be <hi>Norma Officii,</hi> which is not <hi>Norma Judicii,</hi> yet cannot that Law be <hi>Norma Judicii,</hi> which was not before <hi>Norma Officii:</hi> And this Law being not ſuch to any Mortal, but to Chriſt only, it can by no means be unto us a Rule of Judgment. But for the <hi>goſpel,</hi> that the Law thereof is the Rule of Judgment, there is no queſtion with Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> himſelf. <hi>We ſhall be judged by the Law of Liberty,</hi> ſays St. <hi>James,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul, According to my Gospel.</hi> As for the <hi>Sentence</hi> being <hi>one,</hi> there is <hi>Sententia Juris,</hi> and <hi>Sententia Judicis,</hi> and they are one. Such as is the Sentence of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> ſuch will be the Sentence of the <hi>Judge:</hi> And ſuch as will be the Sentence of God at Judgment, ſuch is the Sentence now of every mans Juſtification or Condemnation by the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> Well, and what is <hi>Sententia Juris?</hi> Why this, <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſaved.</hi> And what is <hi>Sententia Judicis?</hi> Why this, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, for when I was hungry you fed me.</hi> That is, you that have believed ſo as your Faith hath wrought by love, or performed the condition of the Goſpel Covenant, I do declare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94653:15"/>you righteous according to <hi>that Law,</hi> and I do adjudge you to there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that I by my Satisfaction and Merit have procured for you, of Pardon and Salvation. Here is the Doctrine of Juſtification accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Book of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> made good, and here is the farther Notion about the Mediatorial Law, being alſo the Rule of Judgment laid aſide; ſo that I may here deliver my ſelf in Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> words (<hi>p.</hi> 121, and 122.) and take my reſt. <hi>By one Rule of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Justifying Sentence is pronounced upon Chriſts Righteouſneſs, and that of a believing ſinner, ſo long as the one Rule of Judgment is the Goſpel promiſe of the Redeemer, He that believes ſhall be ſaved. Hereby the Justifying Sentence does directly paſs upon a man as a Believer, and adjudges him to a right in whatſoever the Goſpel promiſes Believers qua ſuch: And conſidering that the chief deſign of the Gospel is to induce fallen ſinners to believe upon a ſuppoſition and aſſurance given that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is already made by our Redeemer, and not now to be made or adjusted: I do confine my thoughts of Justification to this as the alone Rule of Judgments, and ſo long alſo as the account of the final Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment generally ſtates it in this manner, I declare this to be a ſafe and eaſie Method,</hi> and ſo, I ſay, I might leave off.</p>
            <p>But although as to thus much, Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> muſt conſent, (for they are his words applyed to my ſelf) ſo far as concerns his owning the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels being the Rule of Judgment, yet in regard to his conceit of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rule alſo in connexion with it, I muſt not make an end without ſaying ſomething more, and ſomething of moment. I uſe the word <hi>[confine]</hi> after him, becauſe he has it, he having this conceit, but I who conceive that conceit of his to be vain, ſhould, inſtead of ſaying <hi>I confine my thoughts</hi> (being his words), ſay, I conclude with my ſelf, that it is not only a <hi>ſafe and eaſie,</hi> but the only <hi>Method,</hi> or this Rule is the only Rule of Judgment without the other. As for his three Reaſons for his conceit, I take them to be ſuch, as any man may raiſe for any thing, when he muſt ſay ſomething; and all I have need to ſay, is, <hi>it is no matter for them.</hi> For there is this one thing to be conſidered to make it good which Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſeems not to have laid to his thoughts, which will come in, by and by. There are indeed Divines that will allow no Covenant of Grace but that which was made with Chriſt, or with us in him; and if theſe men who will have but one Covenant, and yet two Conditions, ſo different, as that Chriſt alone was to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the one, and we the other, only they will have <hi>Christ</hi> engaged for the <hi>Elects</hi> performance; if theſe, I ſay, ſhould have framed this Notion, of one Sentence and two Rules of Judgment, it might have appeared ſomething agreeable: But for Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> who diſtinguiſhes theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94653:16"/>Covenants or Laws, and yet puts them together, and connexes both into the Rule of Judgment, it is ſomething monſtrous, eſpcially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath kept ſuch a ſtir about, and laid ſuch a ſtreſs upon the Diſtinction, not conſidering, as I am now to tell, that when he and others do ſpeak of this <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> expreſſing a tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as paſſed between them, in God's requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Chriſt that he ſhall <hi>make his Soul an offering for ſin,</hi> and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him <hi>to have a ſeed,</hi> and that <hi>upon their believing they ſhould be ſaved</hi> (Let them uſe as many or few Words as they will), the whole Frame of this <hi>Covenanting</hi> is made out of the <hi>fifty third of Eſay,</hi> which is a Prophecy of Chriſt to come, telling what he ſhould be, and what he ſhould do, as if it had been already done. Now when this is but a Prophecy, ſo that there is nothing of it, but yet in the <hi>Decree</hi> and Determination of God, and Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſpeaks of this Covenant, as if theſe Matters were all tranſacted before, and apart from the Covenant of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> when the tranſaction I ſay, is but prophecy'd of, and was to be accompliſhed by Chriſt when come, and ſo theſe matters all to be fulfill'd; for then the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> came, and was ſuch a one, and did according as the Prophecy tells, making his Soul an offering for the ſatisfaction of God's Juſtice, and procuring an Act of Grace, Law or Covenant, that thoſe who ſhould become Chriſt's Seed by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſhould be pardoned and Saved (which is really the ſame thing altogether, and no other but what was in the Prophecy:) For Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> (Now I ſay,) who ſeems to have had more conſiderate Thoughts about this Diſtinction than our former Divines, and does indeed ſtill ſpeak ſo riſentively hereof in his Books, as if there could be no ſound Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity about thoſe two great Points of Satisfaction and Juſtification, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the compleat underſtanding and application of it, and does yet further herein <hi>lean</hi> ſo much to his <hi>own underſtanding</hi> as he does, (which <hi>leaning</hi> is ſuch a poſition of the Thoughts, that if the thing leaned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does fail, his notion muſt be all thrown down): I ſay, for him to make two Matters of that which is but one, ſeeing that which was in the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and that which is in the <hi>Fulfilling of it</hi> muſt be the ſame, and intended for the ſame: It gives me juſt cauſe for ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand and Admonition to him, to conſider over and over all ſuch Expreſſions as he has, <hi>p.</hi> 133. where he is apprehenſive, that the want of the conſideration of this Diſtinction, is the cauſe of all our Diſputes, when I am afraid that a <hi>diſtinguiſhing ubi Lex non diſtinguit,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> leaning here ſo much upon this Diſtinction, which I ſuppoſe has been coined but of late by ſame of our own Divines <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Scotch,</hi> and ſcarce to be found one Century ago, (and perhaps not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94653:16"/>come in play till after the <hi>Aſſemblies Catechiſms</hi>) has given occaſion of ſo much roving Fancy, and thereby more Confuſion to himſelf, (and may do through him, if it be not prevented, to others) than ever had like to have been in thoſe great Points without it. I have ſet my ſelf thus, to give him the deeper advertiſement hereof, becauſe I ſee not by any thing, or by all the things, which in this ſeeming notion of his, he is ſtill farther deviſing, that the thing is proved for which it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed. The thing he ſhould ſhew or prove, is an <hi>Imputation</hi> in ſe; but how does his confounding and confounded deviſe prove this? Where hath he laid all his Conceptions together, or any of them alone, ſo clear, as may be an Argument or <hi>Medium</hi> of Probation, (not to put him to <hi>Syllogiſms)</hi> as will evince his Concluſion. When this is wanting, his whole Notion is impertinent, and all his Contrivings abortive: And when any Man writes a Book, and this is wanting, ſo that the <hi>Id quod probandum erat</hi> is not proved, that Author, let him have otherwiſe many good Truths in it, does herein need <hi>Hallebore,</hi> rather than an <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 120. He <hi>finds nothing</hi> (he tells us) <hi>plainer, than that on one hand we are made righteous by Chriſt's Obedience, and on the other, that we are juſtified by Faith,</hi> citing Scriptures on both ſides. This now without ſetting the Scriptures on two ſides, is to be conſider'd, for the Goſpel doth hold forth a double Righteouſneſs, the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Faith,</hi> that do both go to our Juſtification. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his Grace, through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> In another place, <hi>It is of Faith</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>that it may be of Grace,</hi> ſo that our Juſtification by Faith is through Chriſts Redemption, (which is all one as through his Satisfaction and Merit, or through his Righteouſneſs imputed) according to the Goſpel, as the Law or Rule of Judgment. Here now I muſt ask Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſeeing there are two Righteouſneſſes, and each a <hi>juſtifying Righteouſneſs,</hi> (as he ſpeaks in his Books) whether there be alſo <hi>two Juſtifications?</hi> Of this I perceive he is diſcerningly aware, and ſays, <hi>he hopes that none will think he holds ſo,</hi> for indeed, if there were two Juſtifications by theſe two Righteouſneſſes, then the one muſt be a <hi>Legal,</hi> and the other an <hi>Evangelical</hi> Juſtification; and if a <hi>Legal</hi> one, there muſt be a perfect Righteouſneſs to anſwer the Law, and then Chriſt's Righteouſneſs muſt be imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> ſo as to be legally our formal Righteouſneſs, which muſt make Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and I and Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> to retract our Books, and the currant Doctrine of the common Proteſtant run on. But ſeeing he does deny two Juſtifications, you may ask what then does he mean by his <hi>two Laws,</hi> the <hi>Creator</hi>'s Law, and the <hi>Redeemer</hi>'s Law? Why,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94653:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>I had thought when I read his Poſtſcript, this had inferr'd two Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, but now he explains himſelf by fancying only two <hi>Rules of Judgments,</hi> and thoſe not the Law of <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> as others would, but the Law of <hi>Mediation</hi> (though that can not belong to us, as is ſaid before) and the Law of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> when yet there is but <hi>one Sentence,</hi> (according to him) and ſo (which is well) <hi>one Juſtification.</hi> An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Invention this, (which I apprehend but thought not on, till ſince his <hi>Poſtſcript</hi>) but how does he prove it? The Scriptures mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed prove it not, but I think the contrary. Nay, and that he is more concern'd to Anſwer, I ask, what does this prove? If the <hi>Mediatorial Law</hi> were the Rule of Judgment, how would that make Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be imputed ſo, as to become ours <hi>in ſe,</hi> or any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than the Goſpel makes it? Let this be ſhown, let me ſee how his imputation <hi>in ſe</hi> ariſes from it, and from the one more than the other. As for his <hi>Pleadable Security,</hi> I have ſpoke to it already, we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn therefore to the two Righteouſneſſes. That there are two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Righteouſneſſes is out of queſtion, and that Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is juſtifying, and our Faith juſtifying, (by the Virtue and Merit of his) may be received. And if this worthy Brother hereupon had firſt underſtood, and then told us, that though there be two Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſes apart, they make together but one <hi>juſtifying Righteouſenſs,</hi> that is, theſe two Righteouſneſſes are <hi>two parts</hi> of <hi>one whole</hi> Juſtifying Righteouſneſs, according to one Sentence and one Juſtification; he had been happy, and might then have ſpared his making two Rules of Judgment. As for our Faith or Evangelical Righteouſneſs, we declare it merits not our Juſtification nor the benefits of it. It is Chriſt's Righteouſneſs alone has merited the Reward. When we define Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication then to be an Act of Grace, whereby God according to the Goſpel Law (or Rule of Judgment) does account the Believer Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and through the ſatisfaction and merits of our Redeemer does judge him to the Reward of impunity and Life, it is all one as to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to him, or to adjudge him to the participation thereof; for this Impunity and Life being the effects of his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his Righteouſneſs is made ours (when the Effects are) in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe Effects, and can be no otherwiſe imputed to us. When Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> then does tell us of a Righteouſneſs of ours <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to Chriſt's, his meaning is, that our Faith or Evangelical Righteouſneſs, being the conditon of our enjoying the Benefits Chriſt hath purchaſed for us, the performance of the Condition, or this Righteouſneſs Evangelical is required, and muſt proceed in order to our having his Righteouſneſs <hi>quoad hos effectus;</hi> for his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94653:17"/>I have ſaid, is had (or imputed to us) only in our enjoyment of the Effects. To conclude then, our Faith is Juſtifying, or juſtifies us, <hi>per modum juſtitiae conſtituentis:</hi> Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is juſtifying, or juſtifies <hi>per modum Efficientis,</hi> or <hi>per modum meriti.</hi> They both of them are to be put into the Definition, the one I ſay, (when imputed for Righteouſneſs) <hi>per modum cauſae formalis,</hi> and the other <hi>per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum cauſae meritoriae,</hi> concurring (as two-parts of one juſtifying Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs) to the Sinners juſtification.</p>
            <p>I have done, and now what remains, but that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to retract his Notion, and that I offer him my Reaſons for it, which are as follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place let us conſider his <hi>Notion,</hi> which is this, that <hi>God adjudges the Believer to be one, whoſe abſolution, adoption and glory were promis'd to Chriſt in reward of his Death, by the Covenant of Redemption; and for his actual Intereſt and enjoyment thereof, and alſo acceptance and treatment, as a righteous Perſon againſt all Challenges, God judicially accounts what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered to be his plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Security. This we take to be Imputation.</hi> The former part here is matter of fair ful and proper Words, but as for the latter part, where the point is toucht, this ſeems to me ſtrange. Chriſt's Obedience is the Believers <hi>Pleadable Security,</hi> when he ſhould aſſert it to be the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> Is an imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs for <hi>a pleadable Security,</hi> and Imputation of it <hi>in ſe?</hi> Who does not ſee this to be contrary, and the thing we ſtand upon? That which Chriſt hath done and ſuffered, is through Gods promiſe (whether to Chriſt, or us) a Security which we may plead with God for our Pardon and Salvation upon our believing, but is <hi>Chriſts performance</hi> therefore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>in ſe</hi> for <hi>our performance?</hi> What is that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> takes for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation? Is it not the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever? And is the imputing of Chriſts <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to be the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and to be his <hi>Pleadable Security</hi> (that is an Imputation of it to that Effect) all one? My Neighbours honeſty and faithfulneſs is my Security that ſuch a Debt ſhall be paid me; but is his honeſty and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity therefore <hi>in ſe</hi> my honeſty and faithfulneſs? O ſtrange that my Reverend Brother ſhould be ſo intoxicated with this Notion, even ſo as to be out of his ſenſes, and take one thing for another! I pray is not the Point between us and the Brethren this, Whether Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs be imputed <hi>in ſe</hi> for our Juſtification? And is the Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs to us for our <hi>Pleadable Security</hi> our <hi>Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</hi> Gods judicial imputing Chriſts Righteouſneſs to a perſon <hi>in ſe</hi> does juſtifie him: Could his imputing it to him (if there were any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94653:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch thing) for his Pleadable Security, and not for his Righteouſneſs, which <hi>in ſe</hi> denotes) juſtifie him? How does his Notion come up to the Point of Juſtification? As for what he adds, that God <hi>does Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially account</hi> what Chriſt hath done ſuffered to be the Believers Pleadable Security, it is as a man that is not only intoxicated, but plays bold pranks. This is indeed ſaid ordinarily by ſome Divines, that Chriſt doth <hi>judicially account</hi> what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered to be <hi>our Righteouſneſs,</hi> that anſwers the Law, and juſtifies us. Now for Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> to invert this <hi>judicial proceſs</hi> of God to his <hi>Pleadable Security,</hi> and then ſay, <hi>This we take for Imputation,</hi> it ſeems to me ſuch an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious impoſing upon his followers, ſuch a piece of confidence (in ſo momentous a Point) as it is not to be endured.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An Imputation <hi>in ſe</hi> does neceſſarily infer Chriſt to be our <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> which overturns the whole Doctrine of Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and I, and Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> It is impoſſible God ſhould account Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be another mans <hi>in ſe,</hi> but <hi>Legally;</hi> and if it be ours <hi>Legally,</hi> then muſt he be our <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> and ſo have acted and ſuffered in our ſtead <hi>as ſuch.</hi> The Lord Chriſt now we acknowledge did ſuffer and dye for us, or in our ſtead in this ſenſe, that we might not dye or ſuffer, upon our believing, but not that God ſhould account us to have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and done what he did. That is, he acted only as our <hi>Mediator.</hi> To ſuffer, that we might not ſuffer, and to ſuffer, that his ſufferings ſhould be accounted ours, are contradictory things; ſo that by no means Chriſt muſt not be accounted our <hi>Legal Perſon</hi> in what he did and ſuffered for us. In this Point it was Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> broke looſe from the common Doctrine; and he that holds an Imputation <hi>in ſe,</hi> (unleſs this new-fangle be ſo with us) muſt break from him. An <hi>Impuation in ſe</hi> makes the Believer in <hi>Law-ſenſe</hi> as righteous as Chriſt, and ſo brings in all the conſequences of Antinomianiſm, which may be ſeen if Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. From thoſe two Reaſons thus at firſt laid down. I argue; Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is another <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> which Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> has found out, or, either the Imputation <hi>in ſe</hi> which Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> has made out by his new Notions, is really a true <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> or elſe an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> muſt be denied. But the Imputation <hi>in ſe</hi> which Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> thinks he has made out by his new Notion, is nothing but a meer imagination thereof, and not true Imputation <hi>in ſe,</hi> and therefore an Imputation <hi>in ſe</hi> muſt be denied. The <hi>Major</hi> appears, and is confirmed by my <hi>ſecond</hi> Reaſon, and the <hi>Minor</hi> by my <hi>firſt</hi> laid down.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is apparent to all that are diſcerning, that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> does agree with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and me in our Opinion ſo far as concerns the <hi>Brethren,</hi> that is, that in the ſenſe of the <hi>Imputation</hi> they hold, he is againſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94653:18"/>them as much as we, and unleſs what he hath invented be another, there is no other <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> but theirs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The going about to cover this Agreement with us by his new deviſed Notion, which none elſe ever had, or yet underſtood, and that which will never hold, muſt needs betray him to a deeper cenſure than he deſerves, and lay him but the more open to any Pen that ſhall be employed to expoſe him. Not that I call this <hi>New Notion</hi> only a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> if it prove the thing he counts it to do; but ſo long as it proves it not, it is no other.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is not for a man of gravity to play the Child, which hides its head in the Mothers Apron, and thinks that no body ſees him; as if the Vail of this perplexed Conception ſhould be a ſafeguard to Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> againſt the Aſſaults of any Enemy, which it is like rather to provoke, and will afford him no more <hi>Armour</hi> againſt them than a <hi>Cobweb,</hi> which every <hi>Waſp</hi> (and ſuch he muſt look for) will break through, when ſome ſilly <hi>Flies</hi> are entangled with it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The only thing that he can ſay to excuſe himſelf to good men (when they ſee his Notion inſignificant), and which perhaps does ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie him fully now, is that by this Deviſe he does prevent, or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prevent, the <hi>Offence</hi> of the <hi>Weak Brethren,</hi> who are not able to digeſt <hi>ſtronger Meat:</hi> But here will be the Queſtion, Whether he does not herein ſymbolize with <hi>Peter,</hi> who for fear of diſpleaſing the <hi>Jews</hi> by eating with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> did really ſcandalize the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, and made <hi>Paul</hi> reprove him. Let Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> examine this to the bottom, it concerns him, not me, for he muſt give an account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to God.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He does a kind of open wrong to me, and Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> by giving occaſion to ſuch as have a regard to him, or his Books, to account <hi>us Heterodox,</hi> while he ſets <hi>himſelf</hi> and the <hi>Brethren</hi> on one ſide, and <hi>us</hi> upon the other, even in that wherein he agrees with us, but only that he is warpt by his Notion, that makes nothing indeed for the Brethren, nor againſt us, though there were, as he thinks, ſomething indeed in it: Whereas if he did ſtand by us as of his Party, it would hearten them, to own us alſo, ſo as it would in time render the <hi>Offence</hi> inſignificant, and the <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> honourable, as the name <hi>Chriſtian</hi> now is, that was otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When the <hi>Brethren</hi> accuſe him for Agreement with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and he inſtead of confeſſing the ſame, does ſay they wrong him (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid the Damſel did in accuſing him for one being with Chriſt) and flies to his Notion, which if it would hold, he ſhould not yet do; for he agrees with us for all that: Is this like a Diſciple of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94653:19"/>who never baulked ſpeaking his mind out of fear of loſs, either of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, Money, or Life.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Caſe is brought in the Conteſts of the preſent day, to a kind of Caſe of <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> whether we are for an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> or <hi>Quoad Effectus;</hi> and if any that are leading men inſtead of a plain own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Truth (as they conceive it) ſhall uſe any ſhift to ſave that Confeſſion (and when there is no need), I cannot but remember (I do not apply) that Text. <hi>Ye are they who justifie your ſelves before men, but God knoweth your hearts: For that which is highly eſteemed among men, is abomination in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. By Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> new Notion, he is not only kept himſelf from the Confeſſion which he is bound to make when brought to it (that is againſt an Imputation <hi>in ſe</hi>) but it does keep others, though they be convinced in their Judgments, and believe as we, from confeſſing or profeſſing the ſame alſo: And if any will not confeſs the Truth as they believe in their heart (if they be put to it) <hi>before men,</hi> when there is no danger but of Credit, how will they confeſs their Faith if there were danger of Life? If a man does ſhrink at being a <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> how will he abide the being a <hi>Martyr?</hi> And how ſhall be that is <hi>Truth</hi> confeſs him before God their Father in Heaven? Not that I would have any think that Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> uſes a phraſe againſt his Judgment; for I believe he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends ſomething verily in his Notion that proves an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> which I apprehend not; when yet that belief does prove him an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, which I do apprehend, and ſignifie ſo much, to prevent my ſinning againſt my Brother, by giving occaſion to any of thinking of him otherwiſe, from what I write.</p>
            <p n="12">12. If any good Chriſtian ſhall ſay to me, I am offended that you and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> deny the <hi>Imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs;</hi> I will anſwer, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and I do hold the Imputation of Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs as much as really can be held, that is, an Imputation as to the <hi>Effects.</hi> If one ſays, unleſs you grant more, he will be offended ſtill; I will ſay again, there is, there can be no ſuch thing as that Chriſts Righteouſneſs ſhould be <hi>really</hi> (or <hi>in ſe</hi>) ours; and when we grant that it is <hi>Relatively</hi> ours, that is, ours in regard to the <hi>Benefits</hi> or <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> (as the Ranſom-money is the Captives in his Liberty) it is all that can be ſaid, or deſired. And if any be offended for all that, then I ſay, <hi>Is he offended? let him alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. As for the phraſe of <hi>Imputation</hi> then, though it be not in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (I mean in regard to <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs</hi>) let no body miſtake us, we allow it. Our Divines do uſe it, Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> may uſe it, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is for it; they wrong him and me if any ſay we are againſt it. But as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94653:19"/>for an <hi>Imputation in ſe,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> will uſe that pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe, and the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with others follow him, this is an <hi>Offence given</hi> of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture than that of <hi>diſpleaſing men;</hi> for in the ſenſe the Brethren and others uſe it, it is an <hi>Error</hi> in Mr. <hi>Ws</hi>'s. own account, and ſo he <hi>does</hi> and <hi>ſays,</hi> that (in <hi>pleaſing men,</hi> there is the danger) which gives them <hi>occaſion</hi> to <hi>Err,</hi> or continue in their <hi>Errour.</hi> This is a real and certainly forbidden ſcandal (which might be ſhewn out of the eighth Chapter of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians</hi>) unto which we muſt not ſay, <hi>Let them alone. Scandalum eſt dictum vel factum minus rectum praebens alteri oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionem ruinae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> conſidering how our Non-conform'd People ſtand af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, who cannot bear the open intelligible (yet more accurate) Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> having found out ſomething (he thinks) as may inable him to hold the Truth and their Affections alſo, by continuing the phraſe of an Imputation <hi>in ſe,</hi> which he would have thought even by us to be allowable, I cannot but take notice of theſe fair ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly innocent, ſmooth tempting words which he has, <hi>p.</hi> 155. the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents whereof comes to this, that it is <hi>wiſe</hi> for him to do as he does, and has done. His words are theſe, That we <hi>contend</hi> with him only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he will not joyn with us in offending the weak, and hazarding Truth by rejecting a phraſe which well explaind, doth properly expreſs what both intend:</hi> Unto which words, forbearing the falſeneſs of them (the hazard of the Truth, and real offence in his Notion, never to be made out, lying on his ſide) I muſt conſcientiouſly reply theſe two things: The one is, that here are words indeed fair, but God looks through them. The other is, that I will therefore lay down this Rule; <hi>Firſt, That which is honeſt, and then that which is wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> by this new-fangled Notion that hath intoxicated him, hath brought ſuch a perplexity on the Doctrine of Juſtification to himſelf, and conſequently to others (if any go to confound themſelves in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him) that he hath done (or is like to do) more hurt in regard to our underſtanding that great Article, than ever he can do good by any Elucidation thereof, until he come to the purgation of himſelf fully and wholly of all this Leaven with which he hath leavend it, and then write ſome new Book, or Books, for the clearing himſelf, and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine he is otherwiſe engaged in againſt his Oppoſers, without it.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Beſides what is ſaid before in reſpect to the brethren, the uſing the phraſe of an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> in general, is uſing a phraſe which is falſe, dangerous, as tempting to Antinomianiſm, and the uſing the ſame
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94653:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtill after this publick notice and canvaſſing, cannot be juſtified by that which is to us an <hi>Equivocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Before I give my laſt Reaſons, it is fit, ſeeing I publiſh this Letter, for preventing of that prejudice, by reaſon of our Difference, which may turn to the diminution of any of that juſt and due eſteem that my ſelf and others have of Mr. <hi>Ws</hi>'s. Worth and Writings, I do ſignifie that the Difference betwixt us is not <hi>De re,</hi> but <hi>De nomine</hi> only. There is nothing that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> or I do urge againſt an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation <hi>in ſe</hi> in that ſenſe as we oppoſe it, but he agrees to it, and preſſes the ſame: And that which he urges, or hath invented for an Imputation <hi>in ſe</hi> in the ſenſe which is his peculiar, it is not by me gainſaid; ſo that the matter is true (for Mr. <hi>Ws</hi>'s <hi>Writings</hi> are no <hi>Romances</hi>) but it proves nothing, there is no <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> can be inferred from it. And ſeeing his <hi>Notion</hi> proves it not, it is <hi>dictum minus rectum,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſcandalum</hi> that muſt be avoided. You may ſay, if your Difference be only <hi>de nomine,</hi> why do you write this Book againſt him? I anſwer, That becauſe it is no more, he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it. The phraſe of the <hi>imputation of Chriſts Righteouſneſs</hi> we allow, which he might contend for: And when I have ſaid before that we allow this, why is not this enough? The phraſe with it <hi>in ſe</hi> alſo, muſt by no means be allowed, for theſe many Reaſons mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, eſpecially for the Real Scandal that is and muſt be in his own uſe of it.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Though the Difference be but <hi>de nomine,</hi> yet ſo long as his Notion holds it not out, if Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> contines to maintain his Notion, and ſhall draw ſome of our Friends to receive it, he will do this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, which he is not aware of, that is, make a Diviſion and Parties among Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> true Followers, who all are againſt the <hi>Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſe</hi> of the Brethren. He and ſome partial men may ſay that I make Diviſion by writing againſt his Notion, but it is his Notion it ſelf (a new Notion) if it be followed by any muſt make it, if I wrote not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I conclude then, that though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Papers have been ſtopt in the Preſs two or three Months upon the deſire of Mr. <hi>Ws</hi>'s Friends, to deliberate about it, they muſt in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience get out, if it were only to prevent (ſo far as I can) this evil, if there were no other.</p>
            <p n="19">19. To knock the Nail quite home, there is nothing can be ſaid to be <hi>imputed</hi> to a Man which he has, unleſs for another thing than what it is, as <hi>Faith</hi> is imputed for <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> Or for another End than that he ſhould have it, as <hi>Sin</hi> is imputed to be <hi>puniſhed.</hi> It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94653:20"/>that for a thing then to <hi>be</hi> a Man's, and to be <hi>imputed</hi> to a Man, that is, to be his <hi>in ſe,</hi> and to be his only to <hi>an end, uſe,</hi> or <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> are two thing, ſo that an <hi>Imputation in ſe</hi> is indeed an <hi>impoſſible;</hi> for that <hi>thing</hi> which is diverſe from another, cannot be the <hi>ſame</hi> with <hi>that</hi> from which it is diverſe. Let Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> then hammer his Notion as much, as long, and how he will, he ſhall make nothing of it, for there is not ſuch thing <hi>in rerum natura</hi> to be made, and this I hope will do. If I have ſaid <hi>otherwiſe</hi> unawares in any Book my ſelf, I revoke it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> therefore, I fear, hath done ill (either ignorantly or wilfully) and doth ill upon theſe ſeveral accounts; and I muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it his duty to retrieve the evil or the hurt he does or hath done by retracting this new-fangled Invention of his as inſignificant to the deciding any Difference among our Brethren, whatſoever Truth it may have otherwiſe, in a plain, open, ſingle-hearted confeſſion of his miſtake in it, that God may have the glory, our Cauſe be ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his <hi>End of Diſcord</hi> indeed fulfilled. Unto this Retractation therefore I do adviſe, admoniſh and call him (and call him publickly, ſeeing private will not do) and take my Text for it out of <hi>Leviticus; Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thy heart</hi> (but thou ſalt love thy Brother in thy heart, which I do) <hi>Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke him, and not ſuffer ſin upon him.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Sheets were prepared to be Printed before <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term, and to come out then. I ſignified my intention of Printing them to Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> thinking that by an Anſwer to my Letter I ſhould ſee his mind how he would take it. he wrote me no Anſwer, ſo that about a Week after I put them to the Preſs, and thought he was indifferent, and like to be concerned no more about theſe Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions than my others on his former Writings: But after two or three Sheets were Printed, or Compoſed, a Friend of his came to one,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94653:21"/>and told me. that ſuch and ſuch Books were coming out againſt Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and he caſt down about it, and that it would be a cruel thing in me who was a friend to fall upon him, when he was like to he Aſſaulted with Enemies. I had moreover a Letter out of <hi>Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, Porſon of Quality,</hi> who wrote, that he <hi>was informed from, ſome worthy hands in</hi> London, <hi>that I was about to write a Book againſt Mr.</hi> Ws. <hi>and he perceived they had rather I ſhould wave it; but he thought good to acquaint me only with what was written, and leave the matter to my prudent determination.</hi> The Reaſon which theſe Worthy <hi>Perſons</hi> (who ſo ever they are) did urge for this was, <hi>left the Diſſenters differing among themſelves, ſhould give advantage at this ſeaſon to ſome as would</hi> (if they could) <hi>deprive: them of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</hi> I was content therefore upon Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> ſpeaking himſelf to the Bookſeller, to let the Book be ſtopt thus long, till he, and his Friend may ſee, there is no ſuch Books coming out againſt him, nor any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of our loſing any Liberty; nor indeed any Controverſie or Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as to the main Doctrine of Juſtification, wherein Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> and I agree with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> but only in regard to a peculiar Notion of his, which I do exagitate only, to get him to retract and relinquiſh it, which ſeeing I could not do by private Advice, I would by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Judgment. For though I could be willing to let the Book be <hi>delayed,</hi> I could not yield to have it <hi>ſuppreſt,</hi> unleſs upon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that I might have half a dozen of the whole Copy Printed out for my Vindication, in caſe I ſhould need it, as knowing that many could not chuſe but have a mind to ſee that Book, which ſome was ſo earneſt to have ſtopt, and not doubting but the moſt of the Judicious of either Party, will be ready to ſubſcribe to the words of the forementioned perſon (unto whom as one ſo well learned, and ſtudied in the Point, a deference may be paid) which I will ſet down for the conviction of Mr. <hi>Ws</hi>'s. Friends (who may do more with him than I) ſeeing the publication can do that perſon no hurt, and may do Mr. <hi>Ws.</hi> good. His words at the end of his Letter to me are theſe; <hi>I am of Opinion Mr.</hi> Williams <hi>will not be able to anſwer what you ſay; He has endeavoured to go in a middle way between both, but his notion will not bold; He muſt come over to one ſide, or the other.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11 line 7 for prudent read pregnant, p. 13 l. 8 r. <hi>Sydonifts,</hi> l. 33 mend the pointing, p. 17 l. 6 put the Parentheſis at diſobedient, l. 34 for faults 1. fault, p. 20 l. 15 for obliged 1. obeyed, p. 21 l. 12 make the fulpoint after <hi>ſe</hi> a comma, and l. 15 put out the fulpoint after redemption, p. 30 l. 7 for but r. he.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94653:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
